<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Directions for a godly life especially for communicating at the Lord's table. Intended first for private vse; now publish'd for the good of those who desire the safty [sic] of their owne soules, and shall bee pleased to make vse thereof. By H. Tozer Mr of Arts, and fellow of Exceter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Tozer, Henry, 1602-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24161</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122218</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857370</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857370</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23095</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23095)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1190:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Directions for a godly life especially for communicating at the Lord's table. Intended first for private vse; now publish'd for the good of those who desire the safty [sic] of their owne soules, and shall bee pleased to make vse thereof. By H. Tozer Mr of Arts, and fellow of Exceter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Tozer, Henry, 1602-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>198, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Turner printer to the famous Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24161a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Prayer-books and devotions --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Anglican authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23095:1"/>
            <p>DIRECTIONS <hi>FOR</hi> A GODLY LIFE: Eſpecially for Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating at the Lord's Table. <hi>Intended firſt for private vſe; now publiſh'd for the good of thoſe who deſire the ſafty of their owne ſoules, and ſhall bee pleaſed to make vſe thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY H. TOZER M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, and Fellow of <hi>Exceter</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 69.33.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Seke yee after God and your ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> liue.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed by WILLIAM TVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NER Printer to the famous Vniverſity. 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23095:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:23095:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE Gentleman M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> LOREN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZO CARY Sonne to the R. Honourable Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <hi>Faulkland</hi> Lord Deputy of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>WORTHY SIR</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SINCE the time that it firſt pleaſed your honourable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to commend you vnto the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:23095:3"/> religious government of this Colledge, wherein you now liue, your carriage hath beene ſo ſweete &amp; louely, that it hath wonne, I dare ſay, the heart of each member thereof to a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe of reſpecting this your goodneſſe, as in word ſo in deede, according to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places and dignities. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could I ſuffer my ſelfe, ſtanding in a more neare rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than any of the reſt vnto you, to come ſhort in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this office; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I here offer vnto your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious meditation this enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing treatiſe, collected and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:23095:3"/> firſt for private vſe, but now publiſhed; not to gaine the applauſe of any (from which my owne vnworthineſſe ſufficiently checkes mee) but chiefely for theſe two reſpects; first to testifie that loue, which I both owe vnto you and am ready to make good; Secondly and more principally to invite you to a due conſideration of thoſe holy duties therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, that by a ſeaſonable knowledge of the ſame your actions may bee the more carefully ordered, and God's name in the faithfull practiſe thereof more fully glorified.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:23095:4"/> The ſubiect is a matter not of humane learning, but of God's ſervice; and thereof a parte, without exception, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; the due receiving of the holy Communion. A duty, I confeſſe, better knowne, then well conſidered; and more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thought on, then ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſ'd: if it were not ſo, bad actions would not bee ſo commonly priviledg'd by the greatneſſe of the Agents, as now they are; but they to whom God hath giuen moſt honour here, would ever thinke it their greateſt glory to honour him moſt again by their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:23095:4"/> ſervice vnto him. And good reaſon why they ſhould, if they remember that to whom God hath given moſt, of them hee requireth moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; yea ſuch, who haue the precedency of others in place and dignity, may do well to conſider, that, in making a conſcience of matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and leading their liues according to the rules thereof, they doe not onely provide well for the ſalvation of their owne ſoules, but giue a good occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to others alſo, while they happily provoke them to the practiſe of the ſame duties by
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:23095:5"/> their good examples: which are ever held as liuely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and ſerue for a ſecret reproofe to an ingenuous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour, when hee ſhall ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe defectiue in that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his betters haue gone be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. Let the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable &amp; Mighty thus remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how farre they ſhall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God by a religious life, and then they cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that it is their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fredome to bee his hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servants. Others, if they pleaſe, may take notice of this perſwaſion; and perhaps they would, if I were not vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:23095:5"/> to adviſe them: but now I ſpeake to you alone, whom I well knowe willing, as freely to make vſe of others helpe, ſo truely to accept of this from mee. Your owne happineſſe you must confeſſe, with thanks to God, that by his providence you liue in that Society, whoſe Religion is as firme as vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; where you cannot ſay you want the rule either of louing precepts or exanple; according vnto which you haue already ioyned with the rest in a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious communicating at the Lords Table. My deſire is to perſwade you to a conſtant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:23095:6"/> perſeverance in what you haue ſo well begunne; that ſo devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your tender yeares, with thoſe which follow vnto the ſervice of th' Almighty, you may againe from him receiue and fully enioy his dayly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, which doth ever attend on thoſe that truely ſeeke him. Some meditations which perhaps may ſerue for your direction, I here preſent vnto your view; in which I free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge almost nothing mine (to prevent the cenſure of a curious Reader) but onely the labour of compoſing;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:23095:6"/> this I now commend to you, and you vnto the bleſſed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of the moſt Higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ever</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours truely in the Lord HENRY TOZER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:23095:7"/>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:23095:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>DIRECTIONS</hi> FOR <hi>THE DVE RECEI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VING OF THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What a Sacrament is and how many there bee.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Sacrament is an outward viſible ſigne of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible grace; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned by God, whereby hee doth ſeale vnto vs his covenant of grace made in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:23095:8"/> the blood of Chriſt, and wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine teſtifie our faith and piety towards him: ſo that it is both a ſigne in reſpect of the thing ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified, &amp; a ſeale in reſpect of the covenant thereby ſealed vnto vs. The word ſacrament doth properly ſignifie an oath, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Souldiers bound themſelues vnto their Generall; whence it is taken to ſignifie that obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby wee tye our ſelues to the bleſſed and ſweete ſervice of Ieſus Chriſt: for hereby wee, as Chriſt's Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, firſt binde our ſelues by promiſe of obedience to fight vnder the Lords banner againſt the world, the fleſh and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell; Secondly we put on the cogniſaunce and Armes, the Colours and marke of Chriſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:23095:8"/> by profeſſing our faith in him, that ſo it may appeare vnto the world to whom wee doe belong.</p>
               <p>Now Sacraments are of two forts. Firſt of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which were 2. firſt Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, ſecondly the Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer. The firſt was ordained for a ſigne of entrance into the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; the ſecond for an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of confirmation of, and continuance in the ſame: both which are now aboliſhed, and in ſtead of them wee now haue the Sacraments of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which are likewiſe 2. firſt Baptiſme anſwerable to Circumciſion; ſecondly the Lord's Supper to the Paſſeover: both ſignified by that water &amp; blood, which iſſued out of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:23095:9"/> ſide of Chriſt, when it was peirced by the ſouldiers on the Croſſe. Of theſe the firſt is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sacrament of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity or entrance, becauſe by it wee are aſſured that wee are receiued into the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and ſo are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate &amp; belong to the flock of Chriſt: the ſecond is called the Sacrament of our growth &amp; perſeverance, whereby wee growe vp in Chriſt, &amp; are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that we ſhall be ſtill kept in this eſtate. So that both are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary; the one to aſſure vs of our entrance into, &amp; the other of our continuance in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Grace; for although that Grace once conferr'd can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee loſt, yet our aſſurance doth often want ſtrengthening
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:23095:9"/> by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our manifold te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, againſt which we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted by the remembrance of Chriſt's death and paſſion: which doth alſo teach vs why the Sacrament of Baptiſme is receiued but once, &amp; the Lord's Supper often; becauſe our birth is ſignified by our Baptiſme, &amp; we can be borne but once; but we dayly ſtand in need of food and ſtrengthening, &amp; therefore we often receiue the Supper of the Lord, that our ſoules may be nouriſhed vnto life everlaſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. II.</hi> What the Lord's Supper is.</head>
               <p>That wee may rightly vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Sacrament of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:23095:10"/> Lord's Supper we muſt know 2. things. 1, what it is; 2, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the due receiving of it.</p>
               <p>For the firſt; the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is a Sacrament, conſiſting of Bread and Wine lawfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated &amp; diſtributed; inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt himſelfe for a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of the Death &amp; Paſſion of Chriſt, &amp; the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which we receiue thereby.</p>
               <p>This inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was at Chriſt's laſt Supper after hee had eaten the Paſſeouer with his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; ſo that it is called a Supper in reſpect of the time of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution; and the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in reſpect of the Author, the Lord Chriſt; as alſo in reſpect of the end thereof, which is partly to ſet forth the Lord's Death, and the ſpirituall foode
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:23095:10"/> therein receiued, namely the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; blood of Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>In this Sacrament wee muſt conſider 2 things. 1. the parts: 2. the end.</p>
               <p>The parts are 2. firſt the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word Signes. Secondly the thing ſignified. The ſignes are either repreſenting, namely the elements themſelues: or apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſignes, which are the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about thoſe elements.</p>
               <p>The elements are 2. Bread &amp; Wine; not Bread only, but both, according to Chriſt's inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and that aſunder, not the Bread dipt in the Wine, as ſome will haue it; becauſe Chriſt's blood was ſhed out of his body for our ſinnes, and wee are to receiue theſe ſignes as repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Chriſt, not whole but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:23095:11"/> wounded and peirced.</p>
               <p>Now Chriſt choſe thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements before any other, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they beſt ſerue to ſet forth Chriſt's Body and Blood; for as Bread by diverſe breakings &amp; preſſings comes to be perfect, yea the chiefeſt, food of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſtill giving a good reliſh, when other things doe not, and is alſo more common to all tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other. So the body of Chriſt by many torments was made the chiefe nouriſhment of our ſouls, remaining alwayes moſt ſweet and pleaſaunt, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all that can receiue him by faith; and as Wine doth cheriſh and comfort vs, ſatiſfie our thirſt, purge away many corrupt humours, &amp; maketh vs bold and adventrous: ſo the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:23095:11"/> blood of Chriſt reviues and gladd's our drooping ſoules, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfieth our ſpirituall thirſt, purgeth vs from all our ſinnes, and maketh vs couragious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all feare of our enimie the Divell; againe as bread is made of many graines into one loafe, and wine of many grapes into one cuppe: ſo wee, partaking thereof, and of Chriſt, by faith, are made one with him as our head, and alſo one among our ſelues as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his body; thus of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements.</p>
               <p>The Actions in this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are of 2. ſorts. 1. of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. 2 of the Communicants. The actions of the Miniſter are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Setting apart, &amp; 2 bleſſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:23095:12"/> of the Elements, whereby is ſignified that Chriſt Ieſus was ſet apart and ſanctified for vs, as it is Ioh. 17.19.3. breaking and powring out, &amp; 4. diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to the Communicants; whereby is ſignified that Chriſt's Body was crucified &amp; his blood ſhed, &amp; that the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits thereof are offered vnto vs, if we haue faith to receiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it is Ioh. 3.15. <hi>He was lifted vp, that whoſoever beleeueth in him ſhould haue life everlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are 2.
<list>
                     <item>1. Taking.</item>
                     <item>2. Eating &amp; drinking.</item>
                  </list> By which is ſignified that they, which receiue benefit by Chriſt, muſt receiue him by faith applying his merits to their owne ſoules, as Ioh. 1.12.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:23095:12"/> 
                  <hi>As many as received him to them he gaue power to become the Sons of God, euen to them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue on his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus of the ſignes; the thing ſignified is the Body &amp; Blood of Chriſt, with the benefits, which wee receiue thereby; namely the ſtrengthening &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing of our ſoules in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our ſins: &amp; this wee receiue, not of the Miniſter (for he giues only the ſignes) but of God himſelfe, apprehending the ſame by our faith; for Chriſt is not ſignified in theſe ſignes as in a picture, but exhibited vnto vs; being himſelfe preſent in the Sacrament, though not corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to the Bread &amp; Wine, yet ſpiritually to our faith; for though <hi>his Body bee in Heaven
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:23095:13"/> and muſt there remayne vntill the laſt day,</hi> as it is Act. 3.2; yet we may feed on him ſpiritually by fayth by applying his death and paſſion vnto our ſinfull ſouls: ſo that there is one vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene Chriſt and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, which is Symbolicall; and an other betweene Chriſt and vs, which is ſpirituall and reall.</p>
               <p>The ends of this Sacrament are twofold: 1 in reſpect of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: 2 in reſpect of our ſelues.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of others, to teſtifie vnto them that faith which we profeſſe; that ſo they ſeeing our readines herein may haue their harts alſo ſtirred vp to ſuch good duties. In reſpect of our ſelues it concernes, either what we haue received fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or what
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:23095:13"/> wee are to returne to God. In the firſt reſpect it ſerueth.</p>
               <p>Firſt for reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of the death of Chriſt; for, <hi>as often as we receiue this, wee ſhew the Lords death till he come.</hi> 1. Cor. 11.26.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for confirmation vnto vs; and that, both of our vnion among our ſelues; as 1. Cor. 10.17. <hi>for we being many, are one Bread and one Body, for we all partake of one Bread:</hi> as alſo of our Communion with Chriſt; for as the Bread and Wine are turned into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of our bodies; ſo wee by faith are vnited vnto Chriſt, &amp; made fleſh of his fleſh; for <hi>his fleſh is meate indeed, &amp; his bloud is drink indeed;</hi> Ioh. 6.55: &amp; for this cauſe it is called the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:23095:14"/>
               <p>In the ſecond reſpect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that which wee are to returne vnto God, it ſerues to teſtifie our thankfulnes to God for his mercy in giuing vs his Son, and in him all things, and aſſuring vs thereof by this Seale: which wee cannot but doe, when we conſider the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he endured for our ſinnes, which were indeed the very nayles and ſpeares that pierced him: and for this cauſe it is called the Euchariſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in it wee offer vp our thankes vnto God; and ſo alſo it may be called a Sacrifice: not that wee doe therein offer vp Chriſt vnto God, (for Chriſt himſelfe at once finiſhed this offering of his Body on the Croſſe) but becauſe we offer vp our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:23095:14"/> thankfull hearts vnto God for his mercy in Chriſt, ſo that it is a ſacrifice, not of Chriſt, but of our thankfulneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Neceſſity of receiuing the Lords Supper.</head>
               <p>THat wee may receiue this Sacrament, as we ought, we muſt conſider 2 things. 1 the Neceſsity; 2 the right manner of receiuing the ſame.</p>
               <p>As for the firſt, wee muſt know that it is not a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different for vs to receiue or not to receiue at our pleaſure, but that wee ought to doe it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:23095:15"/> though not euery Sabboth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the cuſtome obſerued in the Primitiue Church, yet without faile, as often as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is offered; according to the example of thoſe in the Acts, <hi>who continued ſtedfaſt in breaking of bread,</hi> Act. 2.42.</p>
               <p>The Neceſſity of which du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will further appeare, if wee conſider theſe 2 things. 1 the principall cauſe, which often keepes vs from it; 2 the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, which may draw vs vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that, which makes vs backward in the performance of it, is queſtionleſſe the policy of our Arch-enemy, the Diuel; who ſtriues by all meanes to draw vs away, either by a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe neglect of our chiefeſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:23095:15"/> good to feede rather on our owne fooliſh imaginations (as hee did them in the Goſpell, who had rather <hi>ſee their grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, or proue their oxen, than taſte of that Supper</hi> to which they were invited. Luke 14.18.19.) or elſe by a timorous fearefulneſſe of our owne vnworthineſſe to approach vnto ſo holy a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, as this is. And truely, if we could but ſee that this is his doing, wee would by all meanes ſtriue againſt his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; for, who amongſt vs would not endeauour to the vtmoſt, ſo farre to reſiſt his temporall enemy, as that hee ſhould not bee able to hurt him either in body or in goods? and ſhall wee bee more carefull
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23095:16"/> for the preſervation of our earthly bodies, then of our heauenly Soules, which Chriſt Ieſus hath redeemed by his precious bloud? God forbid; we muſt know that God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects more at our hands; and that our ſoules are neuer ſo ſafe, as when they are in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt oppoſition—, and doe that which is moſt diſpleaſing vnto our chiefeſt enemy, the Divell; for the more wee pleaſe him, the leſſe we pleaſe God; &amp; the nearer wee are to him, the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are from God.</p>
               <p>The Motiues which may draw vs to the performance of this duty, are taken from a due conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe 2 things. 1 who it is, which inviteth vs vnto it. 2 what bee the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:23095:16"/> of receiuing or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing.</p>
               <p>Hee which inviteth vs, is God himſelf, whoſe ordinance it is; and who requires it at our hands as a principall part of his ſeruice; and therefore as often as wee omit it, wee may bee ſure that wee offend him; which hee himſelfe teſtified in threatning to <hi>cut off that ſoule from his people, which ſhould for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to keepe the Paſſeouer.</hi> Numb. 9.13: and if ſo, then doubtleſſe the neglect of this Sacrament, wherein Chriſt is ſo fully exhibited vnto vs, is very diſpleaſing vnto him; which is alſo expreſt in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the great Supper, Luke 14.24. <hi>None of thoſe men, which were bidden, ſhall taſte of my
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:23095:17"/> Supper:</hi> Why? becauſe they came not when they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited; and if we refuſe to come when the Lord calls, who knowes whether hee will giue vs life vntill the next invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Let vs therefore take the Lord's offer, while it is to day, leſt wee be cut off before the morrow.</p>
               <p>The next motiue is taken from the conſequents, and that 1 of not receiuing. If wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not, wee offer a twofold injury; the one to Chriſt, the other, to our ſelues.</p>
               <p>To Chriſt 2 wayes. 1 in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning his ordinance, who commaunded his Diſciples to receiue it, 1 Cor. 11.24. and in them vs. 2 in neglecting his loue towards vs; who (as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:23095:17"/> on his death-bedd) in the night that he was betrayed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed this ſeale and pledge of his loue vnto vs, which therefore ought to bee right deare vnto vs, and at noe time neglected when it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered.</p>
               <p>Againe, if wee receiue not, wee injure our ſelues; and that alſo 2 wayes. 1 in reſpect of our name and profeſſion; for, if wee come not when others doe, wee expoſe our ſelues to the cenſure of them, ſhewing that wee are at leaſt negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters, if not contemners of GOD'S ordinance, <hi>who will haue all to come to it</hi> Matt. 26.27: yea that wee haue not the life of a Chriſtian in vs; for <hi>whoſoeuer eateth not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:23095:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:23095:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:23095:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:23095:19"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:23095:20"/> the fleſh of the Sonne of man, and drinketh his bloud, hath no life in him.</hi> Ioh. 6.53.2 we injure our ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the benefites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, for the remembrance of Chriſt's death and paſſion (if duly conſidered) cannot but be a great comfort vnto vs; which we put from vs, as often as we omit the Lords Supper: and thus much wee may aſſure our ſelues, that the Diuell will bee ready to take the leaſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſuggeſt other meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto vs: and what a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing is it for vs to bee exerciſed in our owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures or ſuch like, when others, with whom wee are bound to bee preſent, are reverently ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of their owne ſoules, to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:23095:20"/> feede at the Lords Table? If we ſay that wee are then exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in other good duties, as reading the Word of God or ſuch like; wee muſt know that ſuch duties (good in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues) are not acceptable to God at ſuch times; and who knowes, ſeeing that heerein we neglect the Lords ordinance, how farre he will giue the Diuell leaue to tempt vs, and draw vs away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen from thoſe duties alſo to wicked imaginations?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Conſequents of recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing cannot but invite vs to a conſtant performance of this duty. Now theſe conſequents reſpect either God, or our ſelues. That which reſpects God, is our duty of thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and praiſe, which heerein
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:23095:21"/> wee offer vnto him for his mercy; which is very pleaſant vnto him, and neceſſary to bee performed of vs; becauſe <hi>hee is gracious, and his mercy endureth for euer towards them that feare him;</hi> and how then can wee but with <hi>Dauid,</hi> haue <hi>our hearts rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſing and praiſe him with the beſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that we haue?</hi> Pſ. 108.1</p>
               <p>That, which reſpects our ſelues, is the benefitt which we receiue thereby; which is twofold. 1 Generall. 2 more ſpeciall. The Generall bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitts, which wee receiue by the Lords Supper, are chiefly two.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Aſupply of all our wants; which wee ſhall bee ſure to haue if wee receiue aright; for hee, <hi>which eateth the fleſh of Chriſt, ſhall neuer hunger; &amp; he,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:23095:21"/> which drinketh his bloud, ſhall neuer thirſt,</hi> as Chriſt himſelf hath promiſed: neither need wee doubt of the truth hereof; for, <hi>hee is full of grace and truth;</hi> Ioh. 1.14. &amp; <hi>in him dwelleth all fulnes.</hi> Col. 1.19; &amp; how then can wee want any thing, if wee poſſeſſe him that hath al things?</p>
               <p n="2">2. An excellent rule to our whole life; for when wee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by conſider God's great loue vnto vs, we cannot (if there be any loue &amp; feare of God in vs) but bee carefull to avoyd any thing, which may bee diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vnto him: ſo that hereby our bodies are made more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient vnto our Souls, &amp; our Souls vnto God.</p>
               <p>The ſpeciall benefit, which we receiue by the Lord's Supper,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:23095:22"/> is in regard of our faith; and this againe reſpects either our ſelues and others, or elſe our ſelues alone.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, a teſtifying of our faith vnto others; for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee both ſhew vnto others the faith, which wee profeſſe; and alſo by our example ſtirre them vp to the performance of the ſame duty; in this reſpect therefore it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that wee ſhould often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond reſpect it is a confirmation &amp; increaſe of that faith, which wee haue in vs: wherein wee are to endeauour by all meanes to continue, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> taught the diſciples, Act. 14.22. and beware that wee fall not from our ſtedfaſtneſſe, but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:23095:22"/> 
                  <hi>grow in grace, and in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> as it is 2. Pet. 3.18. whereof wee cannot but bee carefull, if wee conſider our weakenes; for we are euer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Apoſtaſie, and our faith is exceeding weake; as we may plainly ſee by our coldneſſe in prayer and other good duties, by our feare of death, &amp; by our loue of this world: for the ſtrengthening of which Chriſt hath left vnto vs this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a ſpeciall meanes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing thereunto; for the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which our faith taketh hold of, as it is contained in the Word of GOD, ſo it is ſealed vnto vs by this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and therefore Chriſt calls the cupp, <hi>the cupp of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:23095:23"/> the New Teſtament,</hi> becauſe it ſeales vnto vs the Covenant of God in the New Teſtament, accompliſhed in the ſhedding of Chriſt's blood. Now if a King ſhould in pitty and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion ſend a pardon vnder his Seale vnto a poore diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed priſoner; would wee not judge that priſoner vnworthy of the benefitt thereof, if hee ſhould either wilfully refuſe it, or careleſly neglect it? que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe wee would: yet ſuch is our caſe before God, who, as King of Kings, hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs by this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a full remiſsion of all our ſinnes; if wee therefore ſhall either wilfully contemne, or at our pleaſure receiue
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:23095:23"/> this pledge of his loue, what can wee expect at GOD's hands, but a juſt remoueall of this his fauour from vs? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if wee joyne the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our owne weakeneſſe, which ſo much needeth help, with the meditation of God's mercy, who ſo freely giueth it, wee cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our owne miſery, if wee neglect it: wherefore as we feare him, and tender the good of our owne Soules, let vs bee carefull in the due performaunce of this ſo weighty a buſineſſe. But ſome are wont to frame theſe excuſes for their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The often receiuing of this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:23095:24"/> Sacrament may breede a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteeme thereof; and therefore it is ſafer ſometimes to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine. To which I anſwere, that in matters temporall (as pleaſures, and ſuch like) the often vſe may breed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempt, or at leaſt neglect, as it often doth: but in ſpirituall things it rather breeds a greater deſire, becauſe the more we feele and know the goodneſſe of them, the more we ſeeke after them; yet if it ſo come to paſſe, that by often receiuing, we beginne to vndervalue the worth of it; wee muſt conſider that this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect ariſeth not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the often vſe of the thing, but from our corrupt nature; for this Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is God's owne ordinance; alwayes attended with his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:23095:24"/> bleſſing, if rightly receiued; appointed as a meanes to ſtirre vp and encreaſe our zeale and devotion; and therefore it is not likely that it ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. Let not this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore keepe vs from the LORDS Table, but let vs rather come, that it may bee a meanes to encreaſe our pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some will ſay; I am not prepared, and therefore dare not come: but this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede is no excuſe; for wee muſt knowe that wee ought to bee alwayes prepared, our whole life ſhould bee a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall preparation, as to all other good duties, ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to this; being <hi>euer ready when the Lord ſhall call,</hi> as our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:23095:25"/> Sauiour admoniſheth vs, Matt. 24.44.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Others will vrge; I am to take a journey, or to bee imployed in ſuch or ſuch a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe; and therefore I cannot come: Well: if this journey or the like, muſt of neceſsity bee performed, thy excuſe is the ſafer; but if it may bee any way avoyded (as oftentimes it may) aſſure thy ſelfe, this is to preferre thy owne pleaſure before that which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds: a day will certaynely come, wherein wee muſt giue an account for the neglect of the leaſt of God's ordinaunces; and then it will bee ſaid of ſuch Pretences, <hi>Who required theſe things at thy hands?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:23095:25"/>4. Some are wont to vrge; I am not in charity, by reaſon of ſome wrong which hath beene offered to mee, and therefore I ought not to come. This indeede is an excuſe too common: but wee muſt knowe, that if wee bee not in charity, it is our owne fault; for wee ought to bee in charity, and ſtill to preſerue it: and certayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a miſerable thing it is, that wee ſhould <hi>preferre to feede on our owne malice rather than to eate of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi> this is to hurt our ſelues more than wee neede, euen to wrong our ſelues becauſe others haue wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vs; wee ſhould rather ſeeke all meanes of reconciliation,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:23095:26"/> that ſo wee may remoue thoſe impediments of Piety and Religion, and come the more freely to the LORD's Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Some thus pleade for their abſence; I am afrayde to approach vnto the LORDS Table by reaſon of my mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde infirmities, which are in mee, and therefore I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſometimes to refrayne, leſt I come vnworthily, which is a very fearefull thing. It is ſo indeed, but wee muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that our ſtaying away is no comfort vnto vs in this caſe, but rather a meanes to make vs worſe, and to pull downe Gods judgments vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs: wee ſhould rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the goodnes of God,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:23095:26"/> that inviteth vs, promiſing to <hi>refreſh thoſe that are heavy loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with their ſinnes.</hi> Matt. 11.28: not putting vs off for our infirmities; for, <hi>if thero be a willing minde, hee accepteth vs according to that which wee haue, and not according to that which we haue not.</hi> 2. Cor. 8.12. though we want that perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which others haue; yet, if we haue a true deſire to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed by the merites of Chriſt, and haue a ſincere heart before God, hee will accept vs according to this. Whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer therefore the Diuell ſhall tempt thee to draw thee away by the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy own infirmity, cheere vp thy ſelfe with the comfort of the blinde man in the Goſpel, Mar. 10.49
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:23095:27"/> 
                  <hi>be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, behold he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thee:</hi> ſay vnto thy ſelfe; Chriſt Ieſus hath invited me; &amp; hath promiſed to accept mee, if my heart bee ſincere, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and willing; why then ſhould the conſideration of my infirmities keepe mee from it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Others thus reply; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to receiue, but I am conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto my ſelfe of ſome cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinnes which I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted before God, for which I haue not yet ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented; &amp; how then can I par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of this holy banquet in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God? Is it ſo? art thou poore, &amp; yet wilt thou refuſe gold whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is offred vnto thee? who will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pitty thee for thy poverty? art thou deſperately ſick, &amp; wilt thou not ſeek vnto
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:23095:27"/> the Phyſitian for meanes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery? who will the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bemoane thee for thy diſeaſe? Behold, Chriſt Ieſus is the Phyſitian of thy ſoule; as well able to heale it of all it's diſeaſes, as hee did the bodies of thoſe, which came vnto him, of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities: forſake not then this heavenly Phyſitian; but labour by a ſerious repentance to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thy conſcience of thoſe thy ſins, and then come ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily vnto him: it is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Apoſtle, 1. Cor. 11. who biddeth vs to <hi>examine: &amp; then eate,</hi> not goe away; firſt <hi>examine, then eate of this Bread &amp; drinke of this cup:</hi> If thou ſay, I had rather ſtay till the next opportunity, that I may haue the more time to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:23095:28"/> that the longer thou ſtayeſt, the more ſinnes thou wilt run into, and then it will bee ſo much the harder to repent as thou oughteſt: and beſides that, how do'ſt thou know, whether God will giue thee grace and time to repent then or not? hee hath promiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede to haue mercy vpon a ſinner, at what time ſoeuer he ſhall repent; but hee hath not promiſed to giue him grace to repent when he will: Seeke the Lord therefore while hee offereth himſelfe vnto thee, that thou mayſt finde mercy when thou ſeekeſt it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſome in a proud man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner thus excuſe, (or rather ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie) their abſence. I doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſufficiently beleeue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:23095:28"/> whatſoeuer is propoſed in the word of God; and therefore what neede haue I to receiue this Sacrament ſo often, as a ſeale to confirme my faith? it doth no way conferre grace vnto mee; and my faith is ſo firme, that I perſwade my ſelfe I neede not a ſeale to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then it, ſo much as others doe, whoſe faith is weaker; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thinke that I may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times forbeare. But knowe, ô vaine man which thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteſt with thy God, that this is Gods ordinance, a principall part of his ſervice, which therefore ought diligently to to be performed, though it did no way profit vs, even becauſe God had commanded it: yea, when wee haue done all thoſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:23095:29"/> thinges which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded vs, we muſt ſay that <hi>we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſervants, we haue done but that which was our duty to doe.</hi> Luc. 17.10. Beſides, is thy faith ſo ſtrong that it needs no further ſtrengthening? do'ſt thou not daily perceiue in thee a weakeneſſe of vnderſtanding in matters of Piety &amp; Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; a frailty in thy memory, and a continuall diſorder in thy affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions? if not, know thus much; that it is a miſery to want, but a greater miſery not to be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of our wants: &amp; this alſo knowe for a certaine trueth, that when thou findeſt in thy ſelfe either none, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe a ſmall deſire of hearing Gods word and receiuing the Sacraments; know, I ſay, that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:23095:29"/> there is ſurely ſome ſinne or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thee not well repented of, which cloyeth thy ſoule, that it cannot delight in thoſe ſpirituall exerciſes. Let vs therefore endeavour to come to the Lords Table as often as wee are invited; and when wee doe come; let vs take heede that wee come not for faſhions ſake, or to pleaſe men, or in any opinion of our own merit in this action; for this is not a celebration, but a prophanation of the Lords or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, becauſe herein wee ſerue not God but our ſelues; which is a fearefull thing; for God is not as man, that hee ſhould bee deceiued; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeth he as man ſeeth; for man judgeth onely according
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:23095:30"/> to the outward appearance, but God ſearcheth the very heart &amp; reynes; and will one day as certainly puniſh the propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of his ordinance, as the contemners thereof. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as wee ought in the firſt place to be fully perſwaded of the neceſſity; ſo ſhould wee in the ſecond by all meanes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the right manner of receiving; which is the next thing to be conſidered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> The Neceſſity of preparation.</head>
               <p>HE which deſires to receiue at the Lords Table in a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:23095:30"/> right manner, muſt make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of three duties, which are neceſſarily to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A diligent Preparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p n="2">2 A ſeaſonable Meditation in the time of receiuing.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A religious practiſe after the ſame in our liues and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations.</p>
               <p>In the firſt (as before in the matter of receiving) we muſt take notice of a thinges. Firſt, The Neceſſity. 2. The right manner of Preparation.</p>
               <p>The Neceſſity will plainely appeare, if wee conſider theſe 2. things. 1. In whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence it is, that wee are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. 2. The danger which we bring on our ſelues by not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:23095:31"/> being prepared.</p>
               <p>As for the firſt, we are to ſit, and feede in the preſence of the Lord himſelfe. Now if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, even the beſt of vs, ſhould bee invited by a King to his Princely table, hee would bee carefull to preſent himſelfe (if he reverence his preſence) in the beſt manner that hee could, putting on then eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally (if he haue any better than other) his beſt apparell, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſing all thinges in the moſt decent order, that ſo he might be the better accepted: if ſo; with what feare and reverence ſhould wee then approach vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Table of this King of Kinges, when hee inviteth vs? who ſtands there ready attended with his Angels to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:23095:31"/> behold thoſe, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelues; &amp; will ſoone eſpie out that man, who ſhall dare to approach before him, not having on his wedding garment; and what can ſuch expect, but, with the man in the Goſpell, <hi>a caſting out into vtter darkeneſſe?</hi> Matth. 22.12. Neither muſt wee thinke to deceiue the Lord with an hypocriticall out-ſide; for hee looketh not to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward geſture onely, but to the invvard parts of the ſoule: it is not ſo much a cleane hand or curious attire vvhich maketh vs accepted of God, as a pure heart and a cleanſed ſoule, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned vvith faith &amp; repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; vvee may for a time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue mortall men, ſuch as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:23095:32"/> our ſelues: but when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of our hearts ſhall be made manifeſt, then ſhall our hypocriſie, as well as our ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence, bee laid open to our deſtruction. Let vs therefore humble our ſelues before God, and prepare our ſelues aright, that we may eſcape the danger which will otherwiſe fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs; which is the ſecond thing to bee conſidered in the Neceſsity of preparation. The danger of not being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared is particularly ſet forth vnto vs by conſidering the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which wee herein com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and the reward thereof.</p>
               <p>If we come vnprepared, and ſo receiue vnworthily, our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence is no leſſe than to bee <hi>guilty of the Body and Blood of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:23095:32"/> Chriſt.</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. 1. Cor. 11.27. that is, wee offer ſpeciall diſgrace and indignity vnto Chriſt, in not receiving him with that revere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which we ought: which offence, as it is in it ſelfe very hainous ſo it drawes on vs a fearefull pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; for the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> hath pronounced him <hi>accurſed which doth the worke of the Lord deceitfully:</hi> Ierem. 48.10. and if it be ſo in other things, which are of leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what can we expect for the abuſing of this ſo weighty a matter? The Apoſtle ſetteth downe at full the fearefulnes hereof; when he ſaith. 1. Cor. 11.29. that <hi>he, which eateth and drinketh vnworthily, eateth and drinketh his owne damnation:</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:23095:33"/> than vvhich vvhat can bee more terrible? neither is the Scripture ſilent in ſhevving vs the judgements of God vpon ſuch offenders; as vvee may plainely ſee, both in the Old Teſtament, in the ſuddaine death of Vzza for raſh touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Arke; and alſo in the Nevv, in the <hi>binding hand &amp; foote for want of the wedding garment.</hi> Wherefore let the danger hereof moue vs to a carefull preparation, before vvee preſume to come vnto the Lords Table. But ſome may ſay; I perſvvade my ſelfe, that I can by no meanes bee vvorthy to receiue this Sacrament, and hovv then can I receiue vvorthily? it is true, if vvee truely conſider
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:23095:33"/> our ovvne vnvvorthines and the excellency of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vvee cannot by any meanes become vvorthy thereof: but this muſt bee our comfort, that hee is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vvorthy vvhom God in mercy acccepteth as vvorthy; and ſo hee vvill vs, if vvee come vnto him in humility &amp; reverence. Let vs therefore, according to the Apoſtles rule, firſt <hi>trie &amp; examine our ſelues, and then eate of this Supper:</hi> vvhich that vvee may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doe, vvee ought in the next place to take notice of the right manner of prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:23095:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Concerning Examination in generall.</head>
               <p>FOr our better performance of the duty of preparation, we muſt be carefull to ſet aſide a convenient time before the Communion; wherein, laying aſide all other impediments, we ought ſeriouſly to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in three duties. 1. A dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent examination of our fitnes and worthines to receiue. 2. A comfortable premeditation of the benefits, which we are to receiue. 3. earneſt prayer vnto God for a bleſſing vpon our endeavours; that ſo wee may be accepted to receiue thoſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:23095:34"/> benefits.</p>
               <p>In our Examination we are to conſider; 1 To whom this duty belongs: 2 how it is to be performed.</p>
               <p>The firſt wee learne from Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> 1. Cor. 11. who biddeth <hi>every man to trie and examine himſelfe;</hi> ſo that wee our ſelues are to examine our ſelues. Indeede the Miniſters of the word of God, and all ſuch, to whom God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the charge and care of others, ought carefully to trie and examine thoſe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto them; that ſo they may be the more fit: and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours ought alſo willingly to ſubmit themſelues vnto their triall; yea, if it be not offred, to ſeeke their help when they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:23095:35"/> doubt of any thing; that ſo by their directions they may the more cheerefully goe on. Theſe are duties, vvhich God requires at the hands of all; the neglect vvhereof vvill one day fall heavy vpon thoſe, vvhich ſhall faile in the due performance thereof. Yet this is not ſufficient; for vvee are, for the moſt part, full of hypocriſie, ready to hide our ſinnes from others; yea vve are ſo vvitty in iniquitie, that vve can behaue our ſelues ſo ſmoothly, in reſpect of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard ſhevv, that others ſhall finde no fault in vs at all; though notvvithſtanding our conſciences doe all the vvhile accuſe vs of ſome ſins lurking vvithin vs: vvherefore vve are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:23095:35"/> commanded alſo to try &amp; exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine every man himſelf in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
               <p>This Examination muſt be twofold. 1. Generall. 2 Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. In the firſt vve muſt exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ſelues in theſe tvvo things. 1 Whether vvee be in the number of the faithfull or not; vvhich is very needfull to be conſidered, othervviſe vve partake in vaine; for as our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies can receiue no nouriſhing and ſtrengthening from the foode, vvhich vvee daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, vnleſſe they haue ſome life in them before: ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can our ſoules, if they bee voyde of the life of grace, receiue any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort by this ſpirituall food in the Lords Supper;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:23095:36"/> which doth continue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe life, where it findes it; but workes none, where there is none before. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt place diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trie whether Chriſt be in vs or not; of which we ſhall the more fully aſſure our ſelues, if we can finde this perſwaſion in vs, that we (as our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were) <hi>are ſtrangers and pilgrimes here,</hi> Heb. 11.13. <hi>looking for a citty</hi> (as Abraham did) <hi>which hath foundations, whoſe builder and maker is God;</hi> and that wee are <hi>made free from the bondage of ſinne by the Son of God, Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Ioh. 8.36. and ſo with <hi>David, put our whole truſt and rely only on his mercy.</hi> Pſal. 52.9. 2. We are to make tryall of our readines,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:23095:36"/> whether wee bee willing and haue a deſire to partake of the Lords Supper or no. A willing minde God required of thoſe, which <hi>offered any thing for the building of the Tabernacle;</hi> as it is Exod. 25.2. and of thoſe, <hi>which offered him any burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> Levit. 19.5. If ſo in theſe, which were but ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of things to come; much more doth he expect it at our hands in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty, which is the ſubſtance it ſelfe. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet let vs here deceiue our ſelues, thinking that a bare conſent or willing minde is ſufficient; it is an hungry de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and appetite, as well as a willingneſſe, to receiue meate offered; yea that eſpecially,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:23095:37"/> vvhich teſtifieth a good diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in the ſtomacke: &amp; God requireth in all his ſervice (therefore in this alſo) that <hi>wee ſerue him with all our heart, and with all our ſoule.</hi> Deut. 10.12. and <hi>bleſſed are they, which hunger and thirſt after righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, for they ſhall bee filled:</hi> Mat. 5.6. For vvant of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it is, that many, vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they come to the Lords Table, are never the better; becauſe God, as hee inviteth, ſo hee feedeth none but thoſe that <hi>hunger and thirſt:</hi> Iſai: 55.1. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore trie &amp; examine our ſelues vvhether vvee can ſay vvith David. Pſal. 42.1. <hi>Like as the hart deſireth the water brookes; ſo longeth my ſoule after thee, ô God: my ſoule is a thirſt for God,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:23095:37"/> yea even for the liuing God: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall I come to appeare before the preſence of God?</hi> if vve can find this deſire in vs, then happy are vve: if not; let vs humble our ſelues before God, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to vvorke &amp; ſtirre vp in vs the good motions of his ſpirit, that ſo vve may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to ſome meaſure of this thirſt; and from that goe on farther to a particular exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our fitnes to receiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> The Examination of our Knowledge.</head>
               <p>IN our particular Examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (becauſe vve are dull &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant in matters, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne our Saluation, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:23095:38"/> haue, and doe often offend both God and our neighbours; all which are hinderances to the due performance of this duty, wee muſt examine our ſelues in thoſe particulars, which concerne both our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in matters which we ſhould vnderſtand; &amp; our reconciliation with thoſe, whom wee haue offended.</p>
               <p>That, which concernes our information, is a good and wholeſome knowledge of thoſe things, which God hath revealed vnto vs; which is ſo neceſſary, that it is the very ground of all our ſervice of God: for how can we doe the will of God aright, if wee know it not? <hi>Surely that the ſoule be without knowledge, it is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:23095:38"/> not good</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon:</hi> Prov. 19.2. and therefore <hi>God will haue all men to come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the trueth.</hi> 1. Tim. 2.6. without which wee can reape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no comfort vnto our ſelues in any thing that we doe; but are as dead men: for <hi>this</hi> (and this only) <hi>is life eternall, that wee know God and Ieſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent:</hi> Ioh. 17.3. So that without it there is no life: and hence it is that the Lord himſelf complaines Hoſ. 4.6. <hi>My people are periſhed for lacke of knowledge;</hi> &amp; hence it comes to paſſe, that many receiue this Sacrament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any benefit vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, becauſe they are not able to diſcerne of it aright. Wee ſhould therefore all our
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:23095:39"/> life long carefully exerciſe our ſelues in the word of God, that ſo, when we ſhall come to examine our ſelues concerning our Knowledge, wee may the more eaſily, and with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort, trie our fitnes in this reſpect; whether we haue attayned to a competent mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge in the groundes of religion or not. Which that wee may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doe, wee are to make triall of a twofold Knowledge, which wee ought to haue: the one concerning God, the other concerning man.</p>
               <p>Concerning God we are to know, that there is but one, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe, and true God, ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in three Perſons; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther begetting the Sonne; the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:23095:39"/> Sonne begotten of the Father; and the Holy Ghoſt procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from both: which is a miſtery farre exceeding our vnderſtanding; yet ſo ſarre are wee to know and beleeue it, as GOD hath revealed it in his word: and therefore firſt are we to Examine our ſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this knowledge.</p>
               <p>Concerning man we are to knowe, that he was firſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in vprightnes <hi>according to the Image of God.</hi> Gen. 1.27. but afterwards fell through diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and was againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the meritorious death of Chriſt Ieſus. This we are to examine according to the 2 parts of the Word of God, the Law and the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>In the firſt wee ſhall playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:23095:40"/> ſee what wee are in our ſelues, even wretched and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinners, corrupt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedient parents; &amp; that wee haue juſtly deſerved death as a due reward for our manifold ſinnes both originall and actuall; being <hi>carnall, ſold vnder ſinne, by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath</hi> Epheſ. 2.3.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond wee ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what wee are in Chriſt; and what that covenant is, which God hath made vnto man in him for the pardoning of their ſinnes which returne vnto him by repentance, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſame vnto themſelues by faith. So that here we are to knowe 2 things: 1 the meanes of our redemption and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, the Death of Chriſt:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:23095:40"/> 
                  <hi>whom God in loue ſent into the world, to redeeme them that were vnder the lawe, that wee might receiue the adoption of Sonnes: Gal.</hi> 4.5. <hi>&amp; ſo hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> Col. 1.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The meanes, whereby we may apply this vnto our ſelues; namely faith; which is a gift of GOD, begotten and increaſed by hearing the word, and receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Let vs therefore ſeriouſly examine our ſelues, whether wee haue learned out of the Word of GOD our firſt innocency, which wee had by creation: our miſery, which wee fell into by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; and the happineſſe, which wee haue obtained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:23095:41"/> by our ſweete and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed redemption: for in thoſe things ought every one to bee inſtructed, which approcheth vnto the Lords Table.</p>
               <p>Beſides this Knowledge of GOD and Man, wee are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue a particular Knowledge of the Sacrament it ſelfe; where wee are to trye, whether wee doe rightly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Elements from the Lords Body, and the true vſe of them: wherein wee muſt conſider, that the Bread and Wine, (in themſelues ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) beeing ordained of Chriſt, are now become holy; and whereas CHRIST bleſſed this Sacrament at the firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee are to knowe that it is a bleſſed Sacrament; becauſe,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:23095:41"/> whatſoeuer hee bleſſeth, is bleſſed; and that it will bee a meanes of great bleſſing vnto vs, if rightly receiued and whereas Chriſt gaue the ſame after Supper, wee muſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowe, that it was not ordayned to ſatisfie our bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hunger; for, <hi>if any man</hi> thus <hi>hunger,</hi> Saint Paul tells him that hee muſt <hi>eate at home.</hi> 1 Corinth. 11.34. but it was giuen for the refreſhing of our wearied Soules by the commemoration of Chriſt's Death for vs, and of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him: but of this particular Knowledge of the Sacrament, more in the beginning of the firſt chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In this, as in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:23095:42"/> former, wee muſt diligently trye and examine our ſelues; for, except wee knowe all theſe things, wee are not to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take at the Lord's Table; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without it, whatſoever wee doe, is but blinde devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap: VII. The Examination of our repentance.</head>
               <p>THus of our information in matters, which wee ought to knowe. As for our reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, wee are to examine our ſelues in thoſe things, which concerne either God
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:23095:42"/> or our Neighbours; becauſe wee haue and doe often offend both.</p>
               <p>Thoſe, which concerne God, are principally 2. 1 Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance whereby wee teſtifie our harty ſorrow for offending him, with a deſire of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2 Faith; whereby wee take hold on his mercy, for the pardon and forgiueneſſe of them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, wee are to try whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee haue attained to a competent meaſure of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And indeede, if wee truely looke into our ſelues, and conſider that wee muſt one day giue an account for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very idle word, wee ſhal finde matter enough for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, if our hearts bee
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:23095:43"/> not hardned in ſinne. Now, that it is neceſſary to examine our ſelues herein, appeares from this, becauſe without it wee haue noe ground at all for any comfort in CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS; for hee, which is ſtuft with his ſinnes, is noe more fit to receiue Chriſt, than a glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtomake it's meate: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>vnto them that are defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, there is nothing pure.</hi> Tit. 1.15. that is, if through vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, they remaine in their pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions; but <hi>vnto the pure all things are pure;</hi> and <hi>if wee cleanſe our hands and purifie our hearts and ſo draw nigh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, hee will draw nigh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</hi> Iam. 4.8. <hi>as many as walke according to this rule, peace bee vpon them.</hi> Gal. 6.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:23095:43"/> 16. Let vs then <hi>ſearch and trye our waies and turne vnto the Lord.</hi> Lament. 3.40. and put on Davids reſolution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee come to the Lord's Table; I <hi>will waſh my hands in innocencie, O Lord, and ſoe will</hi> I <hi>goe to thy Altar.</hi> Pſalme 26.6. In this examination of our Repentance wee muſt haue reſpect both vnto the time paſt and to come.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the time paſt, wee are to performe 3. due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Carefully ſearch our hearts to finde out our owne corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; that knowing them wee may the better avoyd them which is moſt neceſſary to bee done &amp; that in the firſt place; becauſe it is impoſſible that he
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:23095:44"/> ſhould ſeeke to goe into the right way, which doth not firſt ſee his errour: and thus much wee muſt knowe, that hee that will not ſet his ſinnes before him here to his converſion, ſhall haue them ſet before him hereafter to his confuſion, if wee will needs cover and hide ſinnes, let vs in loue and charity cover the ſinnes of others; for, <hi>Loue co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth a multitude of ſinne.</hi> 1. Pet. 4.8. that is, layeth them not open before men to their diſgrace, who haue committed them; as many doe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to heare other mens faults ript vp to the quicke, but cannot endure to heare of their owne: wee ſhould not ſo much exclayme againſt other
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:23095:44"/> mens ſinnes, but rather bee humbled for our owne, and lay them fully open before our ſelues, that ſoe wee may come to a more ſerious repentance for them. Which I thinke, wee cannot but doe (except wee haue more than ſtony hearts) when wee conſider the torments which CHRIST ſuffred for our ſinnes; and ſee our owne miſery, what wee are in our ſelues: for this muſt needes driue vs vnto God, as a deſperate diſeaſe vnto the Phyſitian; and make vs vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accuſe our ſelues and ſay Pſalme 51.3. <hi>I acknowledge my fault, and my ſinne is ever before mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the chiefeſt meanes, which wee can vſe to come
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:23095:45"/> to the knowledge of our ſinns, are theſe 2. 1 A conntinuall meditation in the Word of GOD, wherein (as in a glaſſe) wee ſhall plainly ſee all our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities. 2 A ſeaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and converſation with ſuch as are themſelues touched with their ſinnes, both which are excellent meanes: and therefore wee ought ſincere- to love the Word of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth diſcover our ſins vnto vs; and diligently read, &amp; excerciſe our ſelues in it, that ſoe wee may come to a full knowledge of it; &amp; alſo harti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly effect and loue thoſe whom we ſe to be thus affected. when wee haue thus conſidered, that wee ought, and how wee may diſcover our ſinnes; let vs exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:23095:45"/> our ſelues whether wee haue thus done in our life paſt or no, giuing thankes to GOD that hee hath at any time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered ſuch or ſuch ſinnes vnto vs: if wee finde that wee haue not thus done (as GOD knowes, wee are all too ſlacke herein) let vs ſeaſonably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vs of this neglect; and bee ſorry that wee haue no ſooner repented; deſiring GOD that hee will bee pleaſed ever more and more to diſcover our ſins vnto vs, that ſoe wee may the better forſake them and ſerue him, as wee ought. Having thus vnfolded our ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, let vs in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place examine; how in ſorrow wee haue humbled our ſelues to GOD for them;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:23095:46"/> for this is that, even our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, which muſt moue God to compaſſion; and wee knowe that <hi>God is nigh vnto them that are of a contrite heart, &amp; will ſaue ſuch as bee of an humble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> Pſal. 34.18. and therefore David, being preſſed downe with the burden of his ſinnes, comforted himſelfe in this ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The Sacrifice of God is a troubled ſpirit; a broken and a contrite heart, O God ſhalt thou not deſpiſe</hi> Pſal. 51.17. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as on the contrary, if wee haue no true ſorrow, if our ſoules be not wounded within vs for our ſinnes, wee cannot expect that either wee or our prayers ſhould be accepted of God; or, that wee ſhall with the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment receiue any comfort to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:23095:46"/> our ſoules if we come not to it with ſorrow for our former tranſgreſſions.</p>
               <p>Now there is a twofold ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: 1 Servile; when wee are ſorry for our ſinnes (as ſome ſervants are, when they haue offended their Maiſters) not becauſe we haue ſinned againſt ſuch a Maſter, but becauſe wee haue thereby made our ſelues ſubiect to the puniſhment due vnto our offence: this is not that ſorrow, which God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth of vs; for it rather driveth vs to diſpaire, than to any pious meditations. 2 Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall; when (like naturall chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) wee grieue for our ſinnes; not ſo much in reſpect of the puniſhment due vnto vs, as that wee haue ſinned
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:23095:47"/> againſt ſo mercifull and louing a Father. This is that true ſorrow, with which wee ought to bee affected: which wee may obtayne two wayes. Firſt by our ſelues. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the helpe of others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
               <p>By our ſelues; and ſoe by the conſideration eſpecially of two things: Firſt who it is that wee haue offended; even GOD himſelfe, who in tender mercy towards vs, gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne to die for our ſinnes: the conſideration of which cannot but worke in vs a true ſorrow, that wee ſhould offend ſo mercifull a God; for what ſonne is there (if he haue in him the affection of a ſonne) but would grieue that hee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:23095:47"/> ſhould offend a Father, which hath been ever loving &amp; kinde vnto him?</p>
               <p n="2">2. The grievouſneſſe of our ſinnes, which wee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; which will plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, if wee conſider them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of our ſelues, how deadly they wound the conſcience; or with reference to others, how infectious they haue beene to them; whom we haue often drawne into the ſame faults, which wee our ſelues haue committed; and ſo haue made them guilty of our ſinnes, and our ſelues of theirs.</p>
               <p>The next meanes, to attaine this ſorrow, is the helpe of other men, who are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues touched with a feeling in this kinde; with whom wee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:23095:48"/> ought to accompany our ſelues, and patiently to accept of their admonitions, ſtill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting them our trueſt frends, which moſt faithfully and roundly put vs in minde of our faults. The hypocrite may eſteeme ſuch as deſire thus to expreſſe their loue, bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie-bodies or the like; but Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids wiſh was that <hi>the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous might ſmite him friendly &amp; reprooue him.</hi> Pſal. 141.5. and whoſoever is a ſound-hearted Chriſtian will ever ſtriue to make the beſt vſe of ſuch, as hee canne. Let vs therefore examine our ſelues, whether wee haue made good vſe of thoſe meanes or not: if we haue not, wee ought to humble our ſelues before GOD for this
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:23095:48"/> neglect alſo; earneſtly beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him that hee will worke in vs true ſorrow for our ſinnes paſt, with deſire of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherevnto that wee may the better moue him, wee are in the next place to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and confeſſe our ſinnes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to GOD; which is the third thing required in our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Confeſſion is ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that without it wee canne expect not pardon at God's hands, but rather ſome judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or other; and therefore Solomon ſayth. <hi>Hee, that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereth his ſinnes, ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, but who ſo confeſſeth and forſaketh them ſhall haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie:</hi> and Saint Iohn perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs herevnto by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of GOD, ſaying; <hi>If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:23095:49"/> our ſinnes, hee is faithfull and iust to forgiue vs our ſinnes, and to cleanſe vs from all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe.</hi> 1. Ioh. 1.9.</p>
               <p>Now in our confeſſion wee are to obſerue eſpecially three things. Firſt what wee are to confeſſe. Secondly to whom. Thirdly how.</p>
               <p>As for the firſt, there is a twofold confeſſion. 1 <hi>Landis,</hi> or of Thankfulneſſe; of which David ſpeaks Pſal. 89.1. <hi>With my mouth will I ever be ſhewing thy truth; yea every day will</hi> I <hi>giue thankes to thee &amp; praiſe thy name.</hi> Pſ. 145.2. Which we are alſo daily to practiſe according to his example: but this is not that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion, which is ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perly meant here in the matter of Repentance. There is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:23095:49"/> another, called <hi>Confeſſio fraudis,</hi> a confeſſion of ſinne; and this wee are to make, if we will truely repent: which ought to bee, not of ſome ſinnes onely, but of all as farre as wee can call them to minde; and eſpecially of thoſe belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and boſome-ſinnes to which wee are moſt addicted: which that wee may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doe, wee ought dayly to renewe the memory of them in our ſelues; that ſo wee may bee the better able faithfully to confeſſe the ſame, as often as occaſion requires.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wee are to confeſſe our ſinnes, not vnto men or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but vnto GOD, who is the ſupreame Iudge of all.
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:23095:50"/> There is indeede a time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in wee may make confeſſion before men; either in publike, before a whole congregation by way of pennance, being by the Church therevnto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; or elſe in private; and that, either, for ſatiſfaction, to our Neighbour, whom wee haue wronged; or for conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to the Miniſter, when our conſciences are troubled. But that confeſſion, which is a part of our Repentance for our ſinnes paſt againſt God, and wherein wee deſire full pardon for the ſame, wee are to make to God alone: for hee it is, who is offended, and hee alone, that canne forgiue our ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Our Confeſſion muſt not
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:23095:50"/> bee of the heart onely, but of the mouth alſo; for God, who made both, expecteth to bee honoured by both; &amp; as both haue bin vncleane before him; ſoe they ought both alſo to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the ſame, that hee may cleanſe and purifie both them, &amp; with them the whole man.</p>
               <p>Againe our confeſſion muſt proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a twofold ground. 1 Hatred of ſinne becauſe by it wee diſhonour GOD 2. Hope of mercy, which is that wee ayme at in our confeſſion; and it muſt further bee quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with ſincerity, with ſhame and ſorrow that wee haue offended ſoe gratious a GOD, leaſt GOD reiect vs as hypocriticall. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:23095:51"/> hencefoorth leaue off cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the faults of other men, and beginne to aggravate our owne; and eſpecially before wee preſume to come to the Supper of the LORD: Let vs take ſome time vnto our ſelues, wherein wee may bee moſt private; and ſhut our ſelues vp in our cloſets, and there humbly on our knees lay open before God thoſe ſinnes, which wee haue committed in our life paſt: and that ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and faithfully; neither di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing the number of them, nor mincing the hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſſe of them for God will not bee mocked. Theſe are things, which wee are to performe in reſpect of the time paſt: as for the time to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:23095:51"/> come, we muſt know, that hee which will truely repent, muſt not only turne from Euill, but alſo turne vnto Good; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hauing confeſſed our ſins paſt with ſorrow for them, we muſt (if wee expect pardon) conſtantly purpoſe for euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by Gods grace, to amend &amp; reforme our liues; reſoluing (as much as in vs lieth) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voide all occaſions, which may draw vs into the like ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and to make better vſe of thoſe meanes which God hath affoorded vs, than wee haue done heretofore; and that by ſo much the more, by how much we haue offended ſo gracious a Father. But of this reſolution of amendment, more in the 12 Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:23095:52"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Examination of our Faith.</head>
               <p>THe Examination of our Faith, is that wherevnto S. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſaying, <hi>examine your ſelues, whether you bee in the Faith or not.</hi> 2. Cor. 13.5. The neceſſity whereof appeareth euen from this, that <hi>without Faith wee cannot pleaſe God in any thing wee doe.</hi> Heb. 11.26. much leſſe in this weighty buſineſſe: yea Faith is ſo neceſſary, that without it wee doe receiue nothing at all, when wee doe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:23095:52"/> receiue; for although with our bodily hands wee receiue the Bread &amp; Wine; yet if we haue not Faith, wee want a hand to receiue the Body and Blood of CHRIST, and the comfort which thence ariſeth vnto our Soules: for how can wee be perſwaded in our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that our receiuing is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God, and that the merits of Chriſt Ieſus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto vs without Faith? it is impoſsible that wee ſhou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ld receiue any more comfort than what wee beleeue; and therefore our Sauiour CHRIST ſayth; <hi>hee that beleeueth on mee, ſhall neuer thirſt.</hi> Ioh. 6.35: therein implying, that hee which doth not beleeue in him, ſhall euer thirſt: yea,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:23095:53"/> which is fearefull; <hi>he which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not, ſhall bee damned.</hi> Mar. 16.16.</p>
               <p>Now that Faith which is here required of vs, muſt not be only a generall faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee beleeue that the Word of God is true, and that God is a juſt Iudge; (for this the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells themſelues beleeue and tremble at it; and well they may, conſidering what is due to them; eternall condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) but wee muſt goe on further to a more ſpeciall kinde of Fayth; and (which they cannot doe) apply the merites of CHRIST, and the promiſes of GOD made therein, vnto our Soules and Conſciences; ſaying with <hi>Iob,</hi> chap. 19. v. 25. <hi>I know that my
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:23095:53"/> Redeemer liueth:</hi> I know, by the knowledge of Faith; or I beleeue; and not only the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of Man, but My Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer liueth.</p>
               <p>Of which that wee may the more fully perſwade our ſelues, wee muſt beleeue; firſt concerning our ſelues, that we are not able, of our ſelues, to do any thing that is acceptable &amp; pleaſing in the ſight or God; <hi>for we haue nothing but what we haue receiued of God,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth, whether good gift, or ability of doing good.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Concerning the meanes of our Saluation, wee muſt beleeue, that the merites of CHRIST'S Death and Paſſion are alone ſufficient for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, without any merits
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:23095:54"/> at all, or ſatiſfaction of ours.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Concerning GOD, wee ought to beleeue, that, if wee truly repent vs of our life paſt, conſtantly purpoſing to lead a new life hereafter, and ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe thoſe good meanes, which hee ſhall affoord vs, hee will then bee mercifull vnto vs in accepting our indeavours through the merits of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Concerning the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wee ought to beleeue; that it is a meanes, ordained of God, to exhibite vnto vs Chriſt Ieſus with his merits, &amp; a ſeale to confirme our Faith. If, vpon conſideration of theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, we can be thus perſwaded of our owne inſufficiency and unworthineſſe, &amp; that yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:23095:54"/> vpon our ſincere humiliation &amp; obedience, God will bee mercifull vnto vs; if we can not only ſay in generall that God is a mercifull Father, and that Chriſt died for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Man; but euery one of vs in particular thus apply vnto himſelfe; I beleeue that God is my mercifull Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that Chriſt Ieſus died to redeeme me as well as any other; all which I ſhall haue plainely confirmed vnto mee in the receiuing of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; wherein (I truſt) God will in mercy accept mee for Chriſt's merits, though of my ſelfe I be vnworthy: if (I ſay) wee can finde that wee are not hypocritically, but ſincerely; not verbally, but hartily, thus
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:23095:55"/> perſwaded; then may wee, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing thus made peace with GOD by our Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, boldly approach vnto the Lord's Table.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Examination of our Charity.</head>
               <p>HAuing examined our ſelues in thoſe former duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, wee are to goe on to another duty, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth our neighbour; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Charity; which is a free for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing of thoſe that haue of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended vs; with a teſtification of the ſame, when occaſion is offered; and a reconciliation of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:23095:55"/> our ſelues to thoſe, whom wee alſo our ſelues haue wronged.</p>
               <p>That wee may be the better perſwaded vnto a due perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this duty, wee are to obſerue 2 things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The motiues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The manner how it ought to be done.</p>
               <p>The motiues, which invite vs to the neceſsity of it, are drawne from the conſideration of theſe 4. things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What wee our ſelues haue done vnto others.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What harme we doe vnto our ſelues by not being in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What they are, with whom we are offended.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whence ſuch wrongs, as
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:23095:56"/> wee receiue, doe primarily come.</p>
               <p>As for the firſt, we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious vnto our ſelues of a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold offence, which wee haue committed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Againſt other men; whom perhaps we haue at ſome time or other more wronged, then they vs; or at leaſt our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences can tell vs, that wee haue beene prone and ready there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, had wee not beene prevented: and how can hee, which hath beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to wrong others, make the moſt of euery wrong offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by others vnto himſelfe? wee muſt heere take notice of the advice of <hi>Salomon</hi> in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe. <hi>Seeke not,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>to haue thy ſeruant curſe thee;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:23095:56"/> for oftentimes thy heart know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that thou thy ſelfe haſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo curſed others:</hi> Eccleſ. 7.22. So alſo, bee not haſty to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the wrongs which others haue done vnto thee; for thy heart can tell thee, that thou thy ſelfe haſt alſo wronged o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If this conſideration prevaile not with vs; let vs conſider in the next place, that wee haue dayly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded GOD farre more than any man can offend vs: and can any of vs expect any mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy from GOD in the forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our debts, if wee ſhew none to others in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by ſmall matters of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence? Small, I ſay; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the greateſt are but
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:23095:57"/> ſmall in reſpect of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which wee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt GOD. Our Saviour CHRIST tolde his Diſciples playnely (and in them vs) Mar. 11.25. <hi>if yee doe not forgiue others their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, neither will your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father forgiue you your treſpaſſes:</hi> which was veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the Parable of the cruell ſervant; who (becauſe hee had no compaſsion on his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſervant, as his Lord had pitty on him) was <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered to the tormentors, till he ſhould pay all that was due;</hi> with this application annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>ſo likewiſe ſhall my Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father doe alſo vnto you, if yee from your hearts, forgiue not euery one his brother their
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:23095:57"/> treſpaſſes.</hi> Matt. 18.34.35. The conſideration whereof, I thinke, is able to moue any good hearted Chriſtian to loue his brethren, though they haue offended him.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Motiue vnto this duety is taken from the conſideration of the harme, that otherwiſe wee bring vppon our owne Soules; which indeede is greater, than either wee can doe vnto others, or they vnto vs.</p>
               <p>This harme is twofolde; 1 Generall; namely, a ſtayne to all the good, which wee haue: for <hi>though wee ſpeake with the tongue of Men and Angels:</hi> though wee
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:23095:58"/> haue all other good gifts, as of <hi>Prophecying, vnderſtanding of myſteries, &amp;c: yet, if wee haue not Charity, wee are nothing:</hi> 1 Cor. 13.1.2. Let vs not therefore boaſt of our learning and other good parts, as long as wee are without Charity; for all is nothing; <hi>no more than a ſounding braſſe or a tinkling cymball.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Particular: and ſo it is an hinderance, 1 to our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; 2 to the right receiuing of the Sacrament. The want of Charity is an hinderance to our Prayers in a twofolde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe, without Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, wee cannot expect to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that which wee pray for; for if wee pray to GOD
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:23095:58"/> to forgiue vs our treſpaſſes, as wee forgiue them that treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe againſt vs, how ſhall wee hope that God will forgiue vs, if wee forgiue not others, which is the condition of our Prayers? to pray for the one, and not to performe the other, is to mocke GOD in our Prayers; or rather, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably to deceiue our ſelues: for, as many haue not becauſe they aske not: ſo <hi>many aske and receiue not, becauſe they aske amiſſe:</hi> I am. 4.3: and ſuch are they which aske without charity; and who knowes how ſoone they may ſtand in neede of GOD'S mercy?</p>
               <p n="2">2. It hinders our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in this reſpect; becauſe
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:23095:59"/> without Charity, wee cannot joyne thoſe, with whom wee are at variance, with our ſelues in our Prayers: which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rule of our Sauiour CHRIST, who biddeth vs to pray; <hi>Our Father;</hi> and <hi>giue vs Our Bread;</hi> and ſo to joyne others with our ſelues in euery Petition: now how can wee heartily pray thus for them, whom wee loue not? our owne conſciences can ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently tell vs, that wee cannot; yea, and that wee often haue beene faulty here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Wherefore, if wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that our Prayers ſhould hencefoorth bee effectuall, let vs follow the counſell, which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> giueth to the Husband and Wife, 1
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:23095:59"/> Pet. 3.7. which is, <hi>to liue together according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, bearing one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that our Prayers bee not hindered:</hi> which, if wee doe, our Prayers ſhall bee much furthered, as CHRIST himſelfe ſayth: <hi>if two of you ſhall agree on earth, as touching the thing that they ſhall aske, it ſhall be done for them of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in Heauen:</hi> Matt. 18.19.</p>
               <p>The want of Charity is an hinderance to our due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of the Sacrament: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sacrament is a Seale of our vnion and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as with CHRIST, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelues: as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth: 1 Cor. 10.16.17.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:23095:60"/> 
                  <hi>The cup of bleſſing which wee bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the Bloud of Chriſt? the bread which wee breake, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt? for wee, being many, are one Bread and one Body, becauſe wee partake of one Bread:</hi> So that, vnleſſe wee bee joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together in loue, wee cannot bee capable of thoſe benefites, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would ariſe vnto our Soules.</p>
               <p>Againe, loue is the very badge, whereby wee are knowne to bee CHRIST'S Diſciples. Ioh. 13.35: <hi>by this ſhall all men know that yee are my diſciples, if yee loue one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi> It is a part of that wedding-garment, wherewith
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:23095:60"/> euery one ought to bee cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, that comes to the Lord's Table. Wherefore, if wee deſire to bee accepted when wee doe come, and there to receiue the benefits of Chriſt's Death and Paſsion, let vs put on the bowels of mercy and compaſsion.</p>
               <p>A third Motiue vnto this duty is taken from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the parties, with whom wee are offended: they are Men, yea Chriſtians as well as our ſelues; ſuch for whom CHRIST died as well as for vs. Shall wee then thinke it hard to ſuffer ſome ſmall wrong at their hands, for whom CHRIST thought it not too much to die? can wee perſwade our ſelues, that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:23095:61"/> there is the loue of God in vs, if wee hate them whom hee ſo loued? <hi>euery one, which lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him that begate, loueth him alſo that is begotten of him:</hi> 1 Iohn 5.1. and whoſoeuer lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him that did redeeme, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him alſo that is redeemed by him.</p>
               <p>The fourth Motiue vnto this duty of Charity is taken from a ſerious conſideration of the firſt originall, whence theſe wrongs proceed, which wee receiue.</p>
               <p>And heere wee may take notice both of the Authour, and alſo of the Diſpoſer thereof. The firſt Authour is not ſo much the party from whom wee receiue the wrong; as the grand-Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:23095:61"/> of both vs and them; the Diuell: who well knoweth, that <hi>a houſe divided againſt it ſelfe cannot ſtand;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtriueth by all meanes to ſet vs at variance among our ſelues, though ſometimes vpon ſmall occaſions; that ſo thereby, hindering vs from the performaunce of good dueties (as the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing or the Sacrament, and ſuch like) which are the meanes of our Saluation, hee may the more eaſily tempt vs to worſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, while others are better exerciſed; and ſo make his ſide the ſtronger againſt vs: and who knowes what power it may pleaſe God to giue him againſt vs at
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:23095:62"/> ſuch times? Wherefore, as we loue our owne ſafety, let vs ſeeke to croſſe him, who thus oppoſeth vs by his temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and if wee will needs bee at ſtrife, let it bee with him, who will neuer bee at quiet with vs, vntill hee haue gotten the vpper hand of vs: which wee may the more eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues vnto; if wee haue reſpect not ſo much to other mens wrongfull acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as to his wicked ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, the cauſe of all; and aſſure our ſelues, that, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp a wrong, wee right our ſelues, and croſſe him; which ſhould bee our chiefeſt ayme.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:23095:62"/>
               <p>Againe, as the Diuell is the Authour of our wrongs: ſo GOD, who is the Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of all things hath a hand in it: who permitteth the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell thus farre to provoke vs: perhaps for the tryall of our conſtancy and patience, or for other ſome ends beſt knowne vnto himſelfe: and, if wee could but ſee, that the finger of GOD is in our Croſſes, wee would patiently anſwere with <hi>David,</hi> Pſalm. 39.10. <hi>I will become dumbe, and open not my mouth, becauſe it is thy doing; and ſo commit our cauſe to him, that hee might make our righteouſneſſe cleare.</hi> Pſal. 37.6.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the chiefeſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues to perſwade vs to this
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:23095:63"/> duty of Loue and Charity; to all which wee may adde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, taken from the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loue of God to vs; <hi>who ſo loued vs,</hi> without any loue receiued firſt from vs, <hi>that he ſent his Sonne to bee a propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our ſinnes.</hi> 1 Iohn. 4.10. whence the Apoſtle gathereth this powerfull con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; <hi>if GOD ſo loued vs, wee ought alſo to loue one another:</hi> verſ: 11. Which that wee may the better doe, let vs in the next place ſee the manner how it ought to bee perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
               <p>Heere wee are to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect both to the time paſt, and alſo to come.</p>
               <p>As for the time paſt,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:23095:63"/> either vvee haue vvronged o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or they vs. If vvee haue vvronged others, vve ought to performe two thinges. 1. vndoe that which vvee haue done, by making reſtitution as farre as in vs lies: according to the example of <hi>Zacheus</hi> Luk. 19.8. who was willing to <hi>reſtore fourefold whatſoeuer hee had taken from any man by falſe accuſation:</hi> ſuch ought wee to bee, ready to make good, whatſoever wee haue taken from any man, and to giue ſatisfaction for any vvrong that vvee haue done. Neither is it ſufficient to bee vvilling thus to make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, vvhen vvee are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved therevnto: but wee muſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:23095:64"/> alſo in the ſecond place ſeeke peace with thoſe, whom wee haue wronged, though wee bee not ask't: which is the Counſell of Chriſt himſelfe: Matt. 5.23.24. <hi>If thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, leaue thy gift before the Altar, and goe thy way; firſt be reconciled to thy brother:</hi> hee ſaith not; ſtay till hee come to thee, or, be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled when he commeth; but goe thou to him. And ſo <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> alſo adviſeth vs Pſal. 34.14. <hi>Seeke peace and enſue it:</hi> ſtay not till it be offered to, or required of thee; but ſeeke it. But perhaps thoſe (whom we haue offended) are farre off, &amp; wee cannot come neere them;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:23095:64"/> or neere, and will not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to vs; what ſhall wee doe in this caſe? Heere wee ought to vſe all meanes that wee can, for the procuring of peace and quietneſſe; but if either occaſion or acceptance bee denyed vs, wee need not doubt but that God will bee pleaſed to accept of our deſire.</p>
               <p>Now, if others haue wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs, wee muſt (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it may ſeeme ſomewhat hard) freely forgiue them; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving even them that hate vs; wherevnto our Saviour Chriſt often admoniſheth vs in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Goſpell; ſaying; <hi>If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther treſpaſſe againſt thee ſeven times a day, thou ſhalt forgiue him: Luk.</hi> 17.4. And againe, <hi>I ſay vnto you, loue your enemies;<pb n="124" facs="tcp:23095:65"/> bleſſe them that curſe you</hi> Matt. 5.44. But ſome one may ſay, ſuch an one hath vvronged me ſo much, that fleſh &amp; blood cannot take it. It is true, if thou conſult with fleſh and blood, it will ſeeme hard to beare the leaſt wrong: but fleſh is not a friend, whom vvee may ſafely conſult; but rather a boſome enemie, whom vvee ought to reſiſt: if vvee aske counſell of Chriſt (whoſe counſell vvee ought and may moſt ſafely follow) hee will bid vs goe and bee reconciled: and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> bids vs to <hi>feede our enemies, and to overcome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill with good:</hi> Rom: 11.21. and <hi>Solomon</hi> can tell vs, that <hi>it is the glory of a man to paſſe over a tranſgreſſion.</hi> Pro. 19.11. As for
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:23095:65"/> revenge, it is not for vs to meddle with it; becauſe the Lord himſelfe ſaith, Deut. 32.35. <hi>To mee belongeth vengeance and recompence:</hi> and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> will aſſure vs, that <hi>to haue bitter envyings and ſtrife in the heart, is wiſdome which deſcendeth not from aboue; but is earthly, ſenſuall, diveliſh: but that wiſdome, which is from aboue, is eaſie to be intreated, and full of mercy:</hi> I am: 3.17. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs greiue at ſuch wrathfull motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aſſuring our ſelues that it is a point of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdome to forbeare; &amp; certainely, if wee can but once find that God hath wrought in vs a readines to forgiue thoſe, which haue wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs, and to pray for their
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:23095:66"/> converſion, wee may eſteeme it an euident ſigne of Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>As for the time to come, that wee may the better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the bond of Charity, wee muſt reſolue carefully to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe 2 ſortes of rules. 1. How wee may keepe peace with others. 2 How others may doe the like with vs.</p>
               <p>As for the firſt, becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may outwardly wrong vs either in word or deede, that wee may in both avoide diſcontent and ſtrife therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wee muſt propoſe vnto our ſelues a twofold rule.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Concerning their words; which is the rule in <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 7.21. namely: <hi>That wee take no heed vnto all words,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:23095:66"/> that are ſpoken:</hi> for this is that, which often ſtirreth vp ſtrife amongſt vs, which otherwiſe might eaſily, and without any prejudice bee avoyded, if men were not too inquiſitiue and ready to take notice of every thing that is ſpoken: and therefore wee ſhould here not entertaine but fleight, yea reject ſuch men, who, vnder pretence of loue vnto vs, will whiſper in our eares, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly informe vs againſt ſuch or ſuch an one; whom <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> calleth <hi>pickthanks, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperers, tale-bearers, ſuch as will ſeparate chiefe friends:</hi> Prov. 16.28. for occaſion of ſeparation may bee giuen (if ſo taken) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven betweene friends; as wee often ſee that he, which is ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularly
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:23095:67"/> affected to another, may haſtily ſpeake ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull wordes of him; which perhaps hee will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently bee ſorry for, and not ſpeake the like againe; yet this ſhall bee enough for the breach of charity, if it bee in the audience or a whiſperer: vvho (to ſpeake the trueth) is a meere incendiary, that will ever bee adding fuell to the fire of contention. Whence Saint <hi>Iames</hi> calls the tongue <hi>a fire, a world of iniquity, that ſetteth on fire the whole courſe of Nature.</hi> I am. 3.6. And <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>without wood, the fire is quenched; and without a talebearer, ſtrife ceaſeth.</hi> Prov. 26.20.</p>
               <p>The ſecond rule, whereby we
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:23095:67"/> may keepe peace with others, is concerning other mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: vvhich is, that we ſo take them (though ſometimes wrongfull) that we be not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily provoked thereby; for a haſty and furious diſcontent vpon ſome ſmall occaſion, doth often breake out to the breach of charity; vvhereas a ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable deliberation vvould mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigate the matter, and ſo co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all in ſilence. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs, that <hi>Charity ſuffereth long, and is not eaſily provoked.</hi> 1. Cor. 13.4.5. If wee can but make true vſe of theſe 2 rules, vve may eaſily, for our parts, liue at peace with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly we muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that others alſo by our
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:23095:68"/> carriage may doe the like with vs: to which purpoſe we muſt take away, firſt a common fault amongſt vs, which is a maine cauſe of ſtrife and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: 2 the occaſion thereof.</p>
               <p>The fault it ſelfe is rayling, ſcandalous and reproachfull ſpeaking: which is ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that few or none (if we looke narrowly into our words) but are conſcious vnto themſelues hereof; but ſo hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous in it ſelfe, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ranketh it with robbery and extortion, 1. Cor. 6.10. ſaying, that <hi>neither theeues, nor revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, nor extortioners ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the kingdome of God;</hi> and ſo pernitious alſo vnto the ſweet ſociety of men; that it is that breath, which often blowes
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:23095:68"/> the coales of contention ſo farre, that they cannot bee quenched againe without blood: and daily experience teacheth vs, that there is no ſuch common cauſe of ſtrife and debate, as ſcandalous termes which are ſo often heard amongſt vs: ſo that, if we can but avoyd theſe, wee ſhall take away the very ground vpon which our wrongfull actions are builded; and therefore Saint <hi>Iames, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching vs</hi> by the name of <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> exhorteth vs <hi>not to ſpeake evill one of another:</hi> I am: 4.11. and Saint <hi>Peters</hi> adviſe is, that <hi>wee lay aſide all evill ſpeakings, and, as new borne babes deſire the ſincere milke of the word.</hi> 1. Pet. 2.1.</p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:23095:69"/>
               <p>Now, that our ſpeach of others may be ſuch as it ought to bee, let vs follow the adviſe of <hi>Solomon;</hi> whoſe counſell is, that <hi>it bee friendly:</hi> Prov. 18.24: <hi>A man that hath friends, ought to ſhew himſelfe friendly:</hi> not vttering any thing; that may tend to their diſgrace; leaſt, by ſuch diſcourteſies, hee looſe their good liking; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endeavour by faire, and courteous ſpeeches, to knit their hearts faſter vnto him.</p>
               <p>Neither yet can we eaſily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyd this fault, vnleſſe in the ſecond place wee take away the occaſion of it; vvhich is a tickling deſire, that moſt men are affected vvith, to heare the faults of other men (though perhaps leſſe than
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:23095:69"/> their owne) laid open and ſpoken againſt: vvhich quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begetteth a ſuſpition of their vvorth, and herevpon vvee too too readily build ſome calumnious report or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. If it ſhall therefore hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen at any time, that vvee heare the ſlips and errours of another; let vs not bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted therein, but rather ſeeke to cover them; for <hi>hee, that covereth a fault, ſeeketh loue:</hi> Prov. 17.9. and not hee, vvhich deſireth to haue them laide open. This is that vvhich vvee ought to doe, both for the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and preſerving of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; vvherein vvee muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily examine our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvee come to partake
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:23095:70"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:23095:70"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:23095:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:23095:71"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:23095:72"/> with others at the Lords Table. If vpon examination wee finde any thing wanting; either that wee are not in cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with others, or others with vs; let vs according to theſe rules ſeeke by all meanes to make good what is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſo come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Of Premeditation and Prayer.</head>
               <p>THus of the firſt thing to be performed in our prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, namely Examination of our owne fitnes to receiue. The ſecond is the Premeditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the benefits, which wee are to receiue: which we muſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:23095:72"/> not omit, that we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be ſtirred vp to ſeeke God, and to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate at his Table with joy and gladneſſe; for there is nothing which makes vs more cold and backward in ſuch duties, than this, that wee haue not ſufficiently taſted how good the Lord is to thoſe which ſeeke him; the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof is alone able to moue any man to a longing deſire after him. Wherefore, hauing ſearched into our own eſtate by a ſerious examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leaſt wee ſhould yet fall backe to a lukewarme care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe of what we are to doe, (to which the Diuell will bee ever ready to tempt vs) and ſo become the more vnfit to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate at the Lords Table,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:23095:73"/> either to Gods glory or our owne comfort, let vs ever quicken our devotion vvith a ſeaſonable premeditation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vvee come, of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits vvhich vvee are to receiue by comming. All which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehended in this one word life; vvhich vve receiue in the Lords Supper, by receiuing Chriſt, vvho is <hi>Life it ſelfe.</hi> Iohn. 14.6.</p>
               <p>Now the life of a Chriſtian is either the life of Grace here, or Glory hereafter.</p>
               <p>The life of Grace (vvhich we obtaine in this Supper) conſiſts of 2 things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A happy freedome from a twofold euill: firſt of ſin; from vvhich vvee are freed by the Death of Chriſt: vvhoſe blood
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:23095:73"/> (if we relie on him) will make our ſinnes (though as red as ſcarlet) to become as white as vvooll.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi rend="sup">l</hi> of Puniſhment; from vvhich Chriſt hath redeemed vs by the ſhedding of his blood; ſo that <hi>there is no conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which are in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Rom. 8.1. vvhence vvee may boldly ſay, <hi>who is hee that condemneth? it is Chriſt that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yea rather that is riſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe, who is even at the right hand of God, making interceſſion for vs:</hi> verſ. 34.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable enjoyment of a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold good.</p>
               <p n="1">1 An inſeparable vnion both vvith Chriſt our head, <hi>from whom nothing ſhall bee able to ſeparate vs:</hi> Rom: 8.38. as alſo
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:23095:74"/> with our brethren &amp; fellow-members in loue and charity; which <hi>Dauid</hi> accounted <hi>a good and ioyfull thing:</hi> Pſal. 133.1.2 A bleſſed ſtrengthening of our faith, whereof this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a ſure ſeale, (as before) whence it ſhall come to paſſe, that wee ſhall bee able to reſiſt the temptations of the Divell, (who ſtriveth by all meanes to make ſhipwracke of our faith and vs) and reply with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 16.9. <hi>I haue ſet God alwayes before mee, for he is on my right hand, therefore ſhall I not fall:</hi> this is that which <hi>will make our hearts glad, and our fleſh to reſt in hope,</hi> as it is ver. 10. which bringeth in a third good, and that not the leaſt, that God vouchſafeth
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:23095:74"/> to his people in this world, namely, Peace of Conſcience.</p>
               <p>This is that which wee are moſt carefully to ſeeke after, and which in the latter end, will bee more worth vnto vs, than ten thouſand worlds of pleaſure which we can enioy: and therefore <hi>Davids</hi> counſell is, <hi>Keepe innocency, and take heed vnto the thing that is right, for that ſhall bring a man peace at the laſt.</hi> Pſal. 37.38. Now wherein can wee better keepe innocency, than by being care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and faithfully exerciſed in Gods ſervice? and what greater comfort of heart, and what greater peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can redound to a poore ſinfull ſoule, than the full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the forgiuenes of his
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:23095:75"/> ſinnes, &amp; his inſeparable vnion vvith Chriſt Ieſus which vve receiue, if vve receiue aright, by receiuing the Sacrament. This is that, beſides vvhich there is nothing in vs that ſhall be able to ſtrengthen &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs againſt our enemie the Diuell, in the day of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture hence; vvho will then be ſure to affright vs with the vglines of our ſinnes (though now in policy he couer them) that ſo hee may, if it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, driue vs to diſpaire of Gods mercie tovvards vs: then (I ſay) by the helpe of a good conſcience, as <hi>Samuel</hi> reſolutely ſpake vnto the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites, 1. Sam. 12.3. ſaying, <hi>Behold, here I am; witnes againſt me before the Lord &amp; before his
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:23095:75"/> anoynted; whoſe oxe haue I ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? whom haue I defrauded? and I will reſtore it you:</hi> ſo ſhall we be able to nonplus our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating enemie, &amp; ſay; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, Satan, here I am, witneſſe againſt mee before the Lord, wherein haue I done thoſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill things which I ſhould not haue done? wherein haue I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted thoſe good duties which I ſhould haue done? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did I at any time diſpaire of Gods mercy, or neglect the ſame? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did I prophane, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe his holy ſabboths? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did I conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne or neglect his word &amp; Sacraments? here I am; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt me: but my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells me to my comfort, that I haue diligently, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my power, performed
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:23095:76"/> what I ought, and therefore thou haſt no part in me. If wee can thus cleare our ſelues, then ſhall wee bee able to ſay with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. Tim. 4.7.8. <hi>The time of my departure is at hand, I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith:</hi> and that which followeth herevpon, is, <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is laid vp for me a Crowne of righteouſnes.</hi> This Crowne is that benefit, vvhich we ſhall receiue, after this life of grace is ended, in the life of glory. In the meane time, vvhile vvee liue here, vvee ſhall receiue, though not this Crowne actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, yet the full aſſurance thereof, beleeuing vvith Saint <hi>Paul, that it is laid vp for vs, which the Lord the righteous
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:23095:76"/> Iudge ſhall giue vs at the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the benefits, which euery true communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant receiueth at the Lords Table: vvherefore (as vve de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to receiue theſe benefits, which paſſe all vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding) let vs carefully meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that vvee may be inflamed vvith the deſire of them.</p>
               <p>But (becauſe all that vvee can doe, is nothing vvithout Gods bleſsing) vvee are in the next place to pray to God, that he vvill be pleaſed to bleſſe our endeavours, and to accept vs in his Sonne; vvhich is the third duty required of vs in our Preparation: vvithout the due performance of vvhich, though othervviſe vvee haue
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:23095:77"/> diligently prepared our ſelues, vve cannot expect to receiue any comfort of ſoule vvith the Bread and Wine; becauſe God onely giueth that vnto vs, and hee is debter vnto no man: let vs therefore ſeeke vnto him by prayer for a bleſſing, vvho is the giuer of all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. This vve ought to doe firſt in priuate, ſetting aſide ſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient times, vvhere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vve may freely betake our ſelues to this duty: but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the morning, vvhen vve are to receiue, vve ſhould riſe early and conſider what wee are to doe that day, namely, ſit at the Lords Table, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be ſure that we conſecrate our ſelues to God by Prayer and good meditations. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:23095:77"/> in publike with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; where wee ought to preſent our ſelues at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beginning, that ſo wee may joyne together in all things which we are to performe, &amp; there at our firſt entra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce powre forth vnto God (as at all other times) this or the like prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord ſtregthen mee againſt the temptations of Sathan who ſtriveth to draw away my heart from thee; &amp; accept the prayers, which I ſhall now make vnto thee through Ieſus Christ our Lord. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which done, joyne with the Congregation in ſuch prayers as are then vſed.</p>
               <p>In both wee are carefully to conſider 2. things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ought to pray;
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:23095:78"/> and that is, not for our ſelues only, but for others alſo, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Counſell of Saint Iames. Chap. 4. v. 16. <hi>Pray one for another;</hi> which wee learne from the patterne of prayer, the Lord's Prayer, left vnto vs by Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 How we ought to pray; &amp; that is, firſt in humility, with a feeling of our owne wants, for which the poore Publican was <hi>rather iuſtified</hi> than the proud Phariſee for his vaine boaſting. Luke 18.14. Secondly in a ſetled &amp; fervent devotion: when wee pray, our mindes ought not to bee fixed on any thing elſe (as many, God knowes, are) for God will haue the whole heart or none. 3. In faith; with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that wee ſhall receiue
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:23095:78"/> what wee aske; for <hi>hee, which wavereth,</hi> that is, not beleiveth, <hi>Let not that man thinke that hee ſhall receiue any thing of the Lord.</hi> I am. 1.7. If we be defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in any one of theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, we aske amiſſe, and ſo ſhall receiue accordingly. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as wee deſire to receiue benefit &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort by the Lord's Supper, let vs ſeeke vnto God for it: &amp; as we hope to haue our prayers heard; let vs pray both for our ſelues &amp; others in true humility, fervencie &amp; devotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; aſſured hope of obtaining.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XI.</hi> Of Meditation at the Lord's Table.</head>
               <p>Having thus fitted ourſelues by examination of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:23095:79"/> ſtate premeditation of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, &amp; prayer for a bleſſing, wee may aſſure our ſelues that wee haue prepared our ſelues for the receiuing of the holy Communion (though by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our weakeneſſe, not in that meaſure, yet) in that right ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as wee ought: and ſo haue performed the firſt duty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of vs, namely diligent preparation; wherevpon wee may boldly &amp; chearefully (o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe not) preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t our ſelues vnto the Lord's Table: where wee are to bee excerciſed in a ſecond duty, namely, a ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Meditation.</p>
               <p>This Meditation muſt bee threefold. 1 Before. 2 In the time of the Conſecration. 3 Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame, or, in the time of Receiuing.</p>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:23095:79"/>
               <p>Before the Conſecration, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Miniſter is going towards the Table, Meditate on theſe 2. things. 1 Seing the table ſpread, &amp; the Elements ſet thereon, we are to conſider, what place we are come vnto; namely the Table of the great King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven &amp; Earth; &amp; that therefore we ought moſt carefully &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently, to behaue our ſelues, both in body by a reverent &amp; ſeemly geſture: &amp; alſo in mind, laying aſide all earthly cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever: and that in a twofold reſpect. 1 Becauſe the place it ſelfe is holy and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to bee propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by any vnſeemely behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; for theſe muſt bee layd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, as GOD commanded Moſes. Exod. 3.5. <hi>Put off thy
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:23095:80"/> ſhoes from off thy feete, for the place whereon thou ſtandeſt, is holy ground.</hi> 2 Becauſe as the place is holy, ſo alſo God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe is there amongſt vs, as he ſayth Matth. 18.20. <hi>Where two or three are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my name there am I in the midſt of them:</hi> Hee is in the midſt of vs, beholding not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our outward geſture but our very hearts &amp; affections; and ready both to reward thoſe that honour him by reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; &amp; to puniſh all ſuch as diſhonour him by prophaning and abuſing his holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: which we ſhall doe if our carriage be not with feare and reverence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When we heare the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſay, <hi>Drawe neere and take
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:23095:80"/> this Sacrament;</hi> wee muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that God by his Miniſter freely inviteth vs to his Table; then let every one lift vp his heart by this or the like eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord, I am not worthy by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of my ſinnes to approach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee; but ſeeing it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thee in mercy to call mee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, in humility &amp; obedience I come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then joyne in prayer with the Miniſter. In the time of the Conſecration wee ought ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to ſettle our mindes on the Elements, &amp; the Actions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the better ſtirring vp of our devotion: &amp; ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate thus. 1. When we heare the Miniſter read the words of Chriſt's Inſtitution, &amp; ſee him
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:23095:81"/> take the Bread &amp; Wine; wee ought joyfully and thankfully to meditate on the great loue of God in ſetting apart his Son for the Redemption of vs his enemies; which is repreſented in the taking of theſe Eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; ſetting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apart to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto vs, as ſeales and pledges of the ſame: joyfully (I ſay) in reſpect of the benefit, which doth thereby come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, &amp; thankfully in reſpect of God's loue, which is greater tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all the harts of men joyn'd in one are able to expreſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When wee ſee the Bread broken and the Wine powred out, we ought to be exerciſed in a twofold meditation. 1 Of comfort; conſidering that the Bread is broken and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:23095:81"/> the Wine powred out, not onely to be the more diviſible to the Communicants, but chiefely to repreſent vnto vs the crucifying of Chriſts Body, and the ſhedding of his Blood for our ſinnes: for <hi>hee was broken for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> Iſai: 53.5. By which is not meant that any bone of him was broken, but that hee was crucified: whence wee ſhould every one of vs gather this comfort, ſaying to our ſoules: <hi>Chriſt Ieſus was broken on the Croſſe, and ſuffred an accurſed death for mee; by whoſe merits, I truſt, I ſhall eſcape the curſe of that death, which is due for my ſinnes vnto mee.</hi> And here by the way wee may take notice how the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:23095:82"/> Papiſts doe erre in delivering whole cakes vnto the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, which repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Chriſt whole not crucified, and ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford the leſſe comfort.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of ſorrow, &amp; that for our ſins; the grievouſneſſe of which was ſuch that they could not bee ſatisfied for, without the pretious Blood of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: theſe were the ſpeares that pierced him to the Soule; that was that, which drew his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Blood from his ſide: and the conſideration of this ſhould breed in vs a harty ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that we ſo vile wretches, as wee are, ſhould thus wound ſo loving a Redeemer: and certainly if wee doe not grieue for thoſe ſins, for which hee hath ſo much ſmarted, wee
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:23095:82"/> may juſtly feare that the ſtupid Earth, the hard rockes, and the darke graues, which trembled, rent, and opened at his death, ſhall one day riſe vp in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt vs &amp; condemne vs. When therefore we ſee the Bread broken &amp;c: let every one thus meditate; <hi>O vile wretch that I am, that I by my ſinnes ſhould thus wound my mercifull and loving Redeemer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the Conſecration, when the Miniſter is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving himſelfe (conſidering that wee are in the preſence of God, who ſeeth our very hearts) wee ſhould power out our ſoules vnto him in this or the like ſoliloquie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Sweete Ieſu, I doe humbly acknowledge with the Centurion
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:23095:83"/> that</hi> I <hi>am not worthy, that thou ſhouldeſt enter vnder my roofe, much leſſe to come and ſuppe and dwell with mee: but ſeeing it is thy good pleaſure to vouchſafe mee this favour, cleanſe mee,</hi> I <hi>beſeech thee, from my ſinnes, that I may entertaine thee in a pure and ſanctified heart, ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then my faith that I may fully rely on thy mercie; comfort mee with thy bleſſed ſpirit &amp; ſo dwell with mee for ever. grant this, O bleſſed Redeemer, for thy mercies ſake, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, before wee receiue, when the Miniſter is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to diſtribute, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the Elements vnto vs (conſidering that Chriſt with all his benefits is offered vnto vs by GOD, as well as the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:23095:83"/> Elements by the Miniſter) let every one meditate thus with himſelfe: <hi>Chriſt with the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of his Death doth now come to ſanctifie and comfort my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soule, in full aſſurance whereof</hi> I <hi>am to receiue theſe ſignes and Seales at the hand of his Miniſter;</hi> And ſo as he ſtretcheth out his hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue theſe, let him lift vp his ſoule in faith with this or the like ejaculation. <hi>Come, Lord Ieſu vnto thy humble ſervant, as my truſt is thou wilt.</hi> This wee are to doe after the Conſecration, before wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue.</p>
               <p>After this in the act of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing wee are to performe theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1 While wee eate the bread,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:23095:84"/> meditate every one thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed Ieſu, I doe heartily beleeue that thou waſt crucified on the Croſſe, and that for mee as well as for any other, and, as I haue now receiued this Bread broken, whereby my Body ſhall bee nouriſhed: So</hi> I <hi>beleeue that</hi> I <hi>haue alſo receiued ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually thy Body crucified with all the benefits thereof; the full pardon of all my ſinnes; and the ſtrengthening and refreſhing of my ſinfull ſoule; this</hi> I <hi>beleeue, Lord, helpe my vnbeleife for thy mercies ſake. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. When wee drinke the wine, and while wee feele it in our ſtomake, wee ſhould thus meditate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt bleſſed Redeemer, I do truly beleeue that thy Blood was
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:23095:84"/> ſhed out of thy Body, as verily as</hi> I <hi>haue receiued this wine apart from the bread; and that for the remiſſion of my ſinnes, as well as any others: &amp; I do alſo beleeue that with this wine I haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thy precious Blood, whereby my ſins are fully waſhed away &amp; my ſoule purified: &amp; that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy promiſe, I ſhall neuer hunger nor thirſt any more; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe with this Bread &amp; Wine</hi> I <hi>haue receiued thy fleſh, which is meat indeed, &amp; thy Blood which is drinke indeed; with which I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly pray thee to cheriſh &amp; nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh my poore ſoule, &amp; to encreaſe in me hearty loue to theſe my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-members, who haue now participated with mee, that ſo we may ſerue thee as we ought, and that nothing may bee able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:23095:85"/> vs from thy loue; which</hi> I <hi>humbly beſeech thee to grant for thy mercies ſake. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chap. XII.</hi> Of Practiſe.</head>
               <p>THis is that, whereon wee ought to meditate in the time of receiuing; which being duly performed, wee ought in the next place to take notice of a religions Practiſe of thoſe things, which are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved afterwards in our life and converſation.</p>
               <p>Theſe things may be reduced to 2 heads: namely, ſuch as we are to do, 1 in the Church. 2 at home.</p>
               <p>In the Church wee muſt
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:23095:85"/> performe 2 duties.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Having ended the former meditations, wee ought each man in particular to giue thanks vnto God for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in this or the like forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O Lord,</hi> I <hi>humbly bleſſe thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly name, for that thou haſt in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vouchſafed to accept mee at this thy Table amongst the rest of thy elect &amp; choſen people; and that thou haſt ſo gratiouſly fed my languiſhing ſoule with the precious body &amp; blood of Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> I <hi>confeſſe, O Lord, that</hi> I <hi>am not worthy of the leaſt of thy favours; but ſeeing it hath pleaſed thee thus to haue mercy vppon mee; giue mee grace,</hi> I <hi>humbly beſeech thee, to walke worthy of this thy mercy in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life to the glorie of
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:23095:86"/> thy holy name, &amp; the ſalvation of my ſinfull ſoule; even for thy mercies. ſake Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. After this every one ought to joyne with the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in praier &amp; thankſgiving, prayſing God for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſoe depart lovingly together with joyfull hearts that God hath ſo gratiouſly entertained vs his vnworthy ſervants.</p>
               <p>After wee are come home, wee are further to take notice of 2. duties.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Meditation; meditating ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly what comfort we haue receiued by being at the Lord's Table. Vpon which conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if we finde any good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in our ſelues, any aſſurance of the forgiueneſſe of our ſins,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:23095:86"/> wee ought by all meanes to cheriſh the ſame by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt's Death &amp; Paſſion for vs; &amp; ſo much the more lift vp our thankfull hearts vnto God for his mercy; as Saint Paul Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exhorteth the Coloſſians, ſaying, <hi>as ye haue receiued Chriſt Ieſus the Lord, ſo walke yee in him; rooted &amp; built vp in him, &amp; eſtabliſhed in the faith, abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therein with thankſgiuing:</hi> Col. 2.6.7. And this is that, which Solomon maketh a true note of a righteous man; that hee will ever bee increaſing thoſe good gifts, which hee hath in him; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaith Prov. 4.18. <hi>The path of the iuſt is as the ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more vnto perfect day.</hi>
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:23095:87"/> When therefore wee ſhall find a little faith, a little loue in vs (as, GOD knowes, the beſt of vs hath little enough) let vs deſire to increaſe it, and to haue our corruptions diminiſhed; for theſe deſires are a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Grace, and a ſigne of a heart well affected: and of this deſire wee cannot make a better tryall, than by conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering whether wee longe to receiue againe the next time; that ſo theſe good beginnings may bee the more perfected.</p>
               <p>But if wee finde not this comfort in vs; let vs ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues, whether there be not ſome ſinne in vs as yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repented of, and whether wee came not ſo well prepared
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:23095:87"/> to the Communion as wee ſhould: if ſo, then ought wee to humble our ſelues before God, with ſorrow for this our negligence: if wee cannot ſee this in vs, but that wee came well prepared; then muſt we patiently waite the Lord's leaſure, and pray earneſtly that he will giue vs the comfort of his Spirit; with full aſſurance that he will grant our requeſt, when it ſhall be beſt for vs.</p>
               <p>The ſecond duty, wherein we muſt be excerciſed at home, is a reſolution or conſtant purpoſe of leading a new life, wherevnto Saint Paul ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly inviteth vs Rom. 6.19. ſaying, <hi>As you haue yeelded your members ſervants to vncleaneſſe, &amp; to iniquity, vnto iniquity even
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:23095:88"/> ſo now yeeld your members ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to righteouſneſſe vnto ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe;</hi> and why? <hi>becauſe being made free from ſinne, and become ſeruants vnto God, wee haue our fruit</hi> (not vnto ſinne, but) <hi>vnto holineſſe.</hi> ver. 22. Shall wee then be made free from ſinne, &amp; become the ſeruants of God, &amp; yet returne vnto ſinne again? God forbid: if we doe ſo, <hi>we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the grace of God in vaine;</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> beſeecheth the Corinthians to take heed of. 2 Cor. 6.1: now what is it but to receiue the Grace of GOD in vaine, when, after we haue <hi>eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the pollutions of this world through the knowledge of our Lord &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, we are againe entangled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with;</hi> &amp;, as the ſow to the mire,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:23095:88"/> returne to our former courſe of life againe? Saint <hi>Peter</hi> will aſſure vs, that <hi>it had beene better neuer to haue knowne the way of righteouſneſſe, than, after wee haue knowne it, to turne from the holy Commaundement deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered vnto vs.</hi> 2 Pet. 2.21. And well were it, if this were duly conſidered of ſome, who thinke it ſufficient to liue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely that day, in which they receiue, (though perhaps they can ſcarce doe that) and preſently afterwardes liue as profanely and looſely as euer they did; but wee muſt knowe that GOD expects a dayly reformation of thoſe, which preſent themſelues at his Table; and, if wee doe not duly conſider of it, wee
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:23095:89"/> ſhall one day with feare and trembling acknowledge it; as Saint Paul plainly tels the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes; ſaying <hi>If wee ſinne wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully after wee haue receiued the knowledge of the trueth, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth no more ſacrifice for ſins, but a certaine fearefull looking for of judgement and fiery indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Heb. 10.26.27.</p>
               <p>Now that we may the better lead a new life before GOD, wee muſt conſider that to the direction of a Chriſtian life 3 things are to be knowne of vs.</p>
               <p n="1">1 What we are to pray for: 2. What wee ought to beleeue. 3. What we are to doe.</p>
               <p>The firſt beeing rightly known, afford's vs a perfect di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection for our Hope: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond for our faith; the third for our Piety.</p>
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:23095:89"/>
               <p>The 1<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> we haue fully ſet down in the Lords Prayer, compoſed by CHRIST himſelfe as a moſt exact rule for all our Prayers.</p>
               <p>The ſecond in the Creed, which containeth the Articles of our Faith, contained in the doctrine of the Apoſtles; called therefore the Apoſtle's Creed.</p>
               <p>The third in the 10. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, written by the finger of God himſelfe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed vnto vs in his holy Word to be our direction both for our holines towardes God and our charity towardes our neighbours.</p>
               <p>Theſe 3 rules of our life (the Lords Prayer, the Creed, &amp; the 10. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts) are dayly repeated of thoſe of the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and more ſimple ſort; but
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:23095:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="167" facs="tcp:23095:90"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:23095:91"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:23095:91"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="170" facs="tcp:23095:92"/> yet (God knowes) not ſo well vnderſtood, as they ſhould be, by diverſe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a greater meaſure of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: neuer did our Land, yea almoſt euery houſe, more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abound with fruitfull and comfortable expoſitions vpon theſe rules, than now they doe; yet who lookes ſo farre into them, as to know thereby the full extent of any of them? Some few indeede there are (whereof GOD increaſe the number) who make a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable vſe of thoſe good meanes of Saluation: whereas others are well content, yea with delight deſire to reade (and that vpon the beſt dayes) vaine and idle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, which are ſo farre
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:23095:92"/> from furthering vs in the way of ſalvation, as that (like tares) they choake the Word of God, and hinder the growth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as wee too often ſee by our dayly experience. There is indeede a time for all things; for pleaſure, as well as profit: but ſhall wee ſpend the beſt of our time, yea (as ſome doe moſt miſerably) the greateſt part of our time in ſuch vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and altogether neglect thoſe good helpes for our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; eſteeming them too plaine and homely, or not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant enough for our witty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, and acute judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Let ſuch know; that they, which thus neglect their owne good, are guilty to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of a twofold crime,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:23095:93"/>1. Of vnnaturall wrong vnto their owne ſoules, in ſtopping their eyes from beholding the light of ſaluation, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would ſhine vnto them; dealing heerein as injuriouſly with themſelues, as Papiſts doe with their deceiued Laity; trayning them vp in ignorance and blind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of a twofold ingratitude: firſt towards thoſe painefull Authours, which (like fruitfull lights) haue ſpent themſelues for the directing of others; whoſe labours doe wel deſerue to be accepted amongſt vs; &amp; wee ſhall proue our ſelues but vnthankfull members of the Church, wherein wee liue, if wee make not that good vſe of
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:23095:93"/> thoſe lights, for which they were intended.</p>
               <p>Secondly (which is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt) wee ſhew our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull towards GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who hath in mercy rayſed vp ſuch meanes for the helping of our infirmities; whereof o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, better deſeruing than our ſelues, haue beene deſtitute. Hauing therefore ſuch helpes ſo freely offered vnto vs, let vs (if wee deſire to liue more righteouſly before God) vſe them more carefully than wee haue done: endeavouring in the firſt place to know what is contained in each Petition of the LORD'S Prayer; that ſo, when we pray, we may know what that is, for which wee pray; and ſecondly, for
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:23095:94"/> our Faith, to know the full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of euery Article thereof; that ſo wee may truely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what that is, which wee confeſſe wee beleeue: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe both of theſe are little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileable, except our piety bee ſuch as it ought to bee, let vs eſpecially bee exerciſed in the Commaundements of GOD; that thereby wee may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what wee are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and what forbidden. Theſe are the direct courſes which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very true-hearted Chriſtian ought to take, &amp; which will one day proue truly comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, when others, vaine and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous, deceiue vs.</p>
               <p>But becauſe our Piety and religious behaiuour is the chiefeſt thing required on our
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:23095:94"/> part vnto the leading of a new life, let vs further ſee what rules wee may yet obſerue for the directing thereof.</p>
               <p>This Piety of ours is ſeene in theſe 2 things. 1 Our Words. 2 Our Workes and Actions.</p>
               <p>As for our words, we ſhould follow the counſell of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Epheſians, which is, that we avoyd in our talke, <hi>all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, all fooliſh talking, &amp; ieſtings which are not convenient.</hi> Epheſ. 5.4: and he giueth a very good reaſon for it. 1 Cor. 15.33. <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euill communications cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt good manners;</hi> &amp; that ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times both in the ſpeaker and hearer. But ſome wil ſay, what? muſt we neuer vſe any pleaſant diſcourſes? no jeſting at all? yes, there is a time for that alſo;
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:23095:95"/> ſo it be, according to the rule of S. <hi>Peter,</hi> ſuch <hi>as God may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be glorified.</hi> 1. Pet. 4.11: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes we may not: ſtirre vp our mindes wee may to an honeſt cheerefulneſſe by civill and modeſt jeſting; but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene and prophane, which S. S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls filthines; vaine &amp; idle, which he termes fooliſh talking, and jeſting, which is not convenient; ſuch, I ſay, <hi>ought not to bee once named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs as becommeth Saints:</hi> for hereby both ſpeaker &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer are often ſtirred vp to looſe &amp; vain geſtures, or at leaſtwiſe to conceiue &amp; think of them, &amp; ſo God's Name is much diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured. Miſerable it is to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue how frequently ſuch ſpeeches doe paſſe for currant vnder the aſſumed titles of
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:23095:95"/> merry diſcourſes: but let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber what our Sauiour Chriſt hath ſaid: Mat: 12.36.37. that <hi>by our words we ſhalbe iuſtified, &amp; by our words we ſhalbe conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, &amp; that euery idle word, which wee ſhall ſpeak, we ſhal giue an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thereof in the day of iudgement:</hi> Muſt we giue an account of our Words, &amp; ſhal wee not then be careful of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Muſt we anſwere for euery idle word, &amp; ſhal we fill vp our diſcourſes with blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies, with obſcene &amp; ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous jeſtings? if we muſt giue an accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, certainly theſe will ly heavy vpon vs: Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs rather with <hi>Dauid</hi> ſet a <hi>watch before our mouth, &amp; bridle vp our lippes, that wee offend not in our tongue:</hi> let vs bee carefull that our words
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:23095:96"/> bee ſuch, as <hi>Salomon</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, Prov. 25.11. <hi>fitly ſpoken, which are like apples of golde in pictures of ſiluer;</hi> that is; ſuch words, as containe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome matter, &amp; are ſpoken in a comely &amp; decent manner, are as acceptable &amp; pleaſant to the eare of a judicious hearer, as ſiluer pictures, adorned with golden apples, are vnto the eye of the beholder.</p>
               <p>For our Workes, we muſt, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> counſelleth, <hi>walk as children of the light, euer pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing what is acceptable vnto the Lord.</hi> Epheſ. 5.8.10: <hi>hauing our converſation honeſt among men, that they ſeeing our good works, may glorifie God thereby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How to direct both our Words &amp; Actions aright, wee
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:23095:96"/> muſt chiefly obſerue theſe 2 things, 1 how to avoyde that which is euill in both; 2 how to ſeeke and obtayne, that which is good.</p>
               <p>To avoyde that which is in euill, 4 rules are eſpecially to be obſerued.</p>
               <p>The firſt concernes the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of euill; namely, that wee watch and pray, according to our Sauiour's counſell and practiſe: Matt: 26.41: <hi>leaſt wee enter into temptation,</hi> and ſo bee drawne away to ſinne againſt God; for of our ſelues wee are prone therevnto, and vnable to avoyde it: and if it goe ſo farre that we be once tempted to ſinne, and feele in vs any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereunto, wee ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to reſiſt this tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:23095:97"/> in the beginning, &amp; reaſon thus with our ſelues; Did not I lately receiue the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, where I had a full pardon of all my ſinnes (paſt) ſealed vnto me, &amp; where I vowed and promiſed to lead a new life before God, how then can I doe this thing, and breake my promiſe with God? I haue put off my coat of ſinne, &amp; therefore I may not (I will not) put it on again: thus ought we to reſiſt temptations at the firſt, leſt they get the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ouer vs.</p>
               <p>The Second rule concernes the occaſions of euil, which we muſt neceſſarily avoyd, if wee deſire to avoyd the euill it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Occaſions are diverſe, but eſpecially theſe 2.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="181" facs="tcp:23095:97"/>1 Idlenes, from which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed many (&amp; theſe ſometimes haynous &amp; crying) ſins which the Son of <hi>Syrach</hi> calleth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>the teacher of much euill:</hi> Ecclus. 33.27. To avoyde this, we muſt be carefull to imploy our ſelues diligently in that vocation, wherein God hath placed vs; for otherwiſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell will be ſure to take an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to tempt euen the beſt of vs: as we ſee in <hi>David,</hi> who was a man after God's owne heart; and yet, when he was walking on the roofe of his houſe (while <hi>Ioab</hi> &amp; the reſt were in the battle) he was te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to commit adultery with <hi>Bathſheba</hi> the wife of <hi>Vriah:</hi> 2. Sam. 11.2. and how many doe we dayly ſee drawne away
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:23095:98"/> to laſciuiouſnes, drunkenneſſe, &amp; ſuch like vices by this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion? Let vs therefore care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully exerciſe our ſelues in our Vocation, that the Diuell may not haue an opportunity to ſet vpon vs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Bad Company, than which, nothing almoſt is more forceable to draw vs away to that which is euill: Let <hi>Ioſeph</hi> but liue in <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Court, &amp; he ſhall ſoone learne to ſweare <hi>by the life of Pharaoh.</hi> Gen. 42.15: and <hi>if Iſrael abide in Shit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim, the people will ſoone commit whoredome with the daughters of Moah.</hi> Numb. 25.1: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD commaundeth his people to <hi>goe out of Babylon, leſt they bee partakers of her ſinnes:</hi> Rev: 18.4. &amp; ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are we parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:23095:98"/> of other mens ſinnes by frequenting their ſociety; yea, (which is miſerable to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) diverſe of ingenuous diſpoſition and ciuill behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, haue by degrees beene drawne away to looſeneſſe and riot, by aſſociating themſelues vnfortunately with vaine and diſſolute perſons. And we may heerein obſerue the policy of our enemy the Diuell; who, when he findeth any man well diſpoſed of himſelfe, and not ready to yeeld to others temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations will beſet him (if hee can poſsibly) with this ſnare, that ſo hee may either by the wicked perſwaſions or bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of others, ſteale away his heart, and allure him to that which is euill: which ſhould be
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:23095:99"/> a forceable Caveat vnto vs, to make vs heedful what compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny we fall into, &amp; with whom wee acquaint our ſelues, if wee haue any care of our ſouls: ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable is the counſell of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> heerein, who adviſeth vs 1 concerning the examples of others, not to comforme our ſelues vnto them <hi>by walking in their wayes, but to avoyde and paſſe away:</hi> Prov. 4.15. 2 Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their allurements, by no meanes to harken vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; <hi>if ſinners intice thee, conſent thou not.</hi> Prov. 1.10. If they ſay; come let vs take our pleaſure in this or that ſort, let vs goe to ſuch a place, where wee may freely doe what we will, <hi>if they thus drawe thee, walke not in the way with them, refraine thy foote
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:23095:99"/> from their paths.</hi> 3 As for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with others, he advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs to <hi>make no friendſhip with an angry man, and with a furious man not to goe.</hi> why? <hi>leaſt thou learne his way, and get a ſnare vnto thy ſoule:</hi> Prov. 22.24.25. Wilt thou avoyd ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ſwearing, &amp;c. then ſhunne that company wherein thoſe vices are practiſed, or elſe thou wilt rather increaſe them in thee. But ſome will ſay; ſuch an one is my familiar friend, and ſhall I leaue him? that will bee taken vnkindly; ſhall I get my ſelfe diſcredite, where I may avoyd it? yes, bee hee neuer ſo neere vnto thee, yet if hee in his courſes forſake GOD, forſake thou him, leſt GOD forſake thee:
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:23095:100"/> yea thou mayſt therein ſhew thy ſelfe a very friend to him in winning him from his euill wayes by thy forſaking of him; for ſo ſayth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3.14. <hi>If any man obey not our word, note that man, and haue no company with him, that hee may be aſhamed:</hi> it may bee when he ſeeth thee leaue him, he will beginne to thinke of his bad life, &amp; ſo bee aſhamed of it, and by degrees leaue it: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaue bad company for their ſakes alſo, as well as thine owne.</p>
               <p>The third rule is, how wee may reſtrayne our ſelues when wee are about to vndertake any ſinfull action: and that is, by ſetting before our eyes this Caveat, <hi>Godſees: for his
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:23095:100"/> eyes are ouer all.</hi> Prov. 15.3. and therefore whatſoeuer we doe, wee ſhould conſider that wee doe it in his preſence: which, being conſcionably conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, cannot but breed in vs both reverence and watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; reverence in reſpect of his Majeſtie; watchfulneſſe in reſpect of his all-ſeeing Eye, that wee offend him not, who will eſpye in vs the leaſt fault, bee it neuer ſo ſecretly kept from the World.</p>
               <p>Againe, conſider how mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God hath euer beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in deliuering thee from this or that danger, from this or that ſinne, whereinto thou muſt neceſſarily haue fallen, if he had not vpheld thee; &amp; then anſweare the Diuell when hee
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:23095:101"/> tempteth thee, as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did his wicked miſtreſſe; <hi>how can</hi> I <hi>doe this wickednes, and ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my God?</hi> God hath been thus and thus mercifulll vnto mee, and ſhall I yet offend him and provoke him to anger? God forbid.</p>
               <p>The fourth rule is for our direction, when wee are fallen into any ſinne; which is this. When we are ouertaken with any ſinne (as who is not euery day) wee ſhould preſently lament it, and not ſuffer it to goe on any further, leaſt it come to a cuſtome, and ſo ſtick faſt in vs: this is a difference which <hi>Solomon</hi> putteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the righteous and the wicked. Prov. 24.16. <hi>A iuſt man</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>falleth ſeuen
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:23095:101"/> times and riſeth vp againe, but the wicked ſhall fall into miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe:</hi> the juſt man, though hee fall into any ſinne, riſeth againe by repentance; but the wicked ſinketh deeper downe, euen to the pit of deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the chiefeſt rules to bee obſerued for the avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that which is euill.</p>
               <p>The next thing, which wee muſt looke into, is, how wee may obtaine that, which is Good. Heere wee muſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally obſerue theſe 2 things: 1 make vſe of al occaſions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: 2 make conſcience of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery good duty. As for the firſt, we muſt firſt, according to the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3.14. <hi>vſe all dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that we may preſſe on towards the mark,</hi> ſtill endeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:23095:102"/> to bee better and better: and when we finde our ſelues deficient in the performance of any good duty (as GOD knowes wee are in all) wee ſhould do the ſame againe and endeavour to performe it more ſervently and ſeriouſly; that ſo we may come to a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meaſure of goodneſſe. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, wee ſhould gladly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of good men, that by their example &amp; adviſe wee may be brought to a ſenſe &amp; feeling of thoſe ſins, which we commit; counting it a great bleſſing of God, if thereby wee at any time be croſt in thoſe ſinnes, to which wee are moſt addicted; as gaming &amp;c: and ever eſteeme beſt of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, not where our eares maybe
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:23095:102"/> filled with prophane jeſtings, or tickled with ſuperfluous conceits; but where our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions may be moſt round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproued; eſteeming them our beſt friends, that will moſt plainly and faithfully put vs in minde of our errours; which is the counſell of Saint Paul to the Theſſalonians; <hi>I beſeech you</hi> (ſayth hee, 1. Theſſ. 5.12.13.) <hi>to know them which labour among you, and are ouer you in the Lord and admoniſh you; and to eſteeme them very highly in loue for their workes ſake:</hi> which may be our direction for eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming both of our familiar freinds and of our teachers; both which (if faithfull) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for our good in the Lord by admoniſhing vs; and both
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:23095:103"/> thereby deſerue from vs a true regard as a recompence of this their loue: therefore if any man deſire to bee furthered in good duties, let him teſtifie it by louing ſuch men.</p>
               <p n="2">2 If wee deſire to obtaine that which is good, wee muſt bee carefull that we make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (as of avoyding every evill, ſo) of doing every good duty, be it neuer ſo little; <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring</hi> with Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>haue alwaies a conſcience voyde of offence toward God and men:</hi> Act. 24.16. and labouring to keepe, not onely ſome but all Gods commandements, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Davids</hi> wiſh, Pſal. 119.5.6. <hi>O that my wayes were made ſo direct, that I might keepe thy ſtatutes, ſo ſhall
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:23095:103"/> I not be confounded, while I haue reſpect to all thy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</hi> Let vs not deceiue our ſelues in thinking it ſufficient, that we obſerue the ſabbath, &amp; that wee offend not God by ſwearing, ſtealing, or ſuch like haynous offences; &amp; yet in the meane time make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a lie for our commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or of vaine and idle diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes for delight; for, if we thus doe, it is certainely an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of a bad heart.</p>
               <p>But ſome perhaps will ſay; If I thus endeavour to carry my ſelfe in all things, if I now and then doe not giue a little way, I ſhall bee accounted too preciſe, and curious in matters which I need not. Bee it ſo; yet bee willing to vndergoe that
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:23095:104"/> cenſure; and eſteeme it ſafer to offend vngodly men by thy good life, than a righteous God by thy bad life: &amp; though others account it too much preciſenes, yet doe not thou ſo; but rather conſider that God commandeth vs <hi>to keepe his precepts diligently:</hi> Pſal. 119.4: if diligently, then certainely there is nothing in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts ſuperfluous; nothing, which we may doe or not doe, but euery one, though of neuer ſo ſmall a matter, is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of vs: whoſoever therefore ſhall endeavour to his power to keepe the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of God in every thing, is ſo farre from being too preciſe, that hee doth but what he is commanded.</p>
               <pb n="195" facs="tcp:23095:104"/>
               <p>To theſe rules, for avoyding of evill and ſeeking of good, wee may adde one more, as the rule of all the reſt, and of our whole life; and that is the Word of God: which alone is able to direct vs in the way to ſaluation, as <hi>David</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: Pſal. 119.9. <hi>Wherewith ſhall a young man cleanſe his way? even by ruling himſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy word:</hi> Wherefore let vs carefully reade, meditate &amp; conferre, about this Word, &amp; that often; accounting (as well wee may) every day loſt, wherein wee learne not ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of it; ever deſiring more &amp; more to be inſtructed therein, and account it a great bleſſing of God, that wee haue the vſe of it ſo freely to direct
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:23095:105"/> vs in the way of ſalvation. Neither let any man thinke himſelfe ſo learned, that hee needeth no farther inſtruction; for the beſt of vs comes ſhort of <hi>David,</hi> and yet hee prayed ſtill to <hi>be inſtructed in the word of the Lord;</hi> as wee may ſee throughout the 119 Pſal. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if wee did know more than wee doe, yet wee are dull in the performance of what wee know; and therefore wee haue neede to reade the ſame againe and againe, to ſtirre vs vp to a daily practiſe hereof. But that wee may ſo vſe the word of God, as that it may bee vnto vs the ſavour of life vnto life; let vs at all times, when wee are about to reade it, lift vp our hearts to God by
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:23095:105"/> prayer, that he may giue a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to our endeavours; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which whatſoeuer we doe in this or any other thing, it will bee ſo farre from being profitable vnto vs, as that it will rather proue our ruine in the end.</p>
               <p>Hee, which ſhall thus ſet his heart to ſerue the Lord by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying vngodlines and worldly luſts, by living honeſtly, righteouſly and ſoberly in this preſent world; he, which ſhall thus carefully receiue the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in a right manner, &amp; heare the word with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, devoting himſelfe to God by prayer in all things, which he doth; he which ſhall thus make conſcience of his wayes in every thing; the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:23095:106"/> of God reſt vpon him, as it needs muſt; and that peace of conſcience, which no man knoweth but he that enjoyes, ever attend him here, and everlaſting peace and happines crowne him hereafter. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:23095:106"/>
            <head>The Contents of each Chapter.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>What a Sacrament is, and how many there bee. pag. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>What the Lord's Supper is. <hi>17.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>The Neceſſity of receiving the Lord's Supper. <hi>27.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>The Neceſſity of Preparation. <hi>54.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23095:107"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Of Examination in generall. pag. <hi>62.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>The Examination of our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>69.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VII.</label>
               <item>The Examination of our Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>78.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. VIII.</label>
               <item>The Examination of our Faith. <hi>98</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. IX,</label>
               <item>The Examination of our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. <hi>104.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23095:107"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Of Premeditation and Prayer. pag. <hi>134.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. XI.</label>
               <item>Of Meditation at the Lord's Table. <hi>147</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. .XII.</label>
               <item>Of Practiſe. <hi>160</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
